<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<plants>
  <id>1</id>
  <title>Plants</title>
  <slug>plants</slug>
  <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
  <plant>
    <id>2</id>
    <title>Amaranth</title>
    <slug>amaranth</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
    <scientificName>Family: &lt;i&gt;Amaranthaceae&lt;/i&gt;, the amaranth family</scientificName>
    <group>Family: Amaranthaceae, the amaranth family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>3</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.12216100 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <annual>1</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>0</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>4</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.14436700 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>5</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.16400200 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>The leaves are good in the summer (usually best early on) and the seeds ripen in autumn, the greatest harvest being in mid-fall.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;</season>
    <habitat>Amaranth grows in fields, disturbed habitats, roadsides, and cultivated areas throughout North America.&lt;br /&gt;</habitat>
    <range>Various species grow throughout the continental US and Mexico.&lt;br /&gt;</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>It's also native to Mexico and Europe. The seeds are so small, a muddy-footed migrating bird blown of course by a storm could have transported it across the Atlantic either way in prehistoric times.</placeOfOrigin>
    <native>1</native>
    <howToSpot>Look for a coarse-looking plant with oval to lance-shaped, long-stalked, medium-sized alternate leaves. Large, dense, coarse clusters of tiny green flower masses are present in mid- to late summer, and similar clusters of seeds in the fall.&lt;br /&gt;</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This group of nearly 40 weedy looking, leafy plants, two to eight feet tall, bears large, distinct, dense, upright spikes of tiny seeds. There's no strong, distinct odor.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The coarse, oval to lance-shaped, long-stalked, alternate, toothless leaves grow from one to two inches long.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thousands of tiny, green, inconspicuous flowers, surrounded by hair-like bracts, create conspicuous, dense masses in the summer. Then thousands of tiny, round, black seeds, also in dense clusters, and surrounded by the papery bracts, cram into the same locations in autumn. </generalInfo>
    <positiveId></positiveId>
    <harvesting>Simply strip off the leaves from young plants. A few pieces of tender leaf stalks and stems are alright to include.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To harvest the seeds, look for amaranth where it's very abundant. Clip off large numbers of seed clusters with garden or kitchen shears, or a pocket knife. Put them in paper supermarket shopping bags and let them dry out a few weeks (you can store them indefinitely that way).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;</harvesting>
    <cooking>I find the leaves are unpleasantly bitter raw, but some people do eat them. Serve them to a raw food enthusiast you don't like.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On the other hand, they're excellent cooked, a little like spinach with overtones of string beans. Add them to soups, stews, sauces (especially tomato sauce), or vegetable dishes. They're also great sautéed or steamed, and strong-tasting enough that you can stir in your favorite spices or sauce in the end, or just serve with salt and pepper and a dash of olive or sesame oil. They cook in about 10 to 15 minutes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rub the dry seed heads (this works with fresh seed heads too, but it's much less efficient) over a bowl to remove the seeds. Transfer to a tray or cookie sheet and blow a fan across the tray over the sink, or outdoors, to get rid of the chaff  (Note: The author and app developer disavow all responsibility for any and all housecleaning bills incurred if the chaff makes a mess in your kitchen). Use the seeds immediately, or store indefinitely in tightly closed jars.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Although not technically a grain, you can cook the nutty flavored seeds as you would a grain: Boil them in water to cover for about 15 minutes, or until the water is absorbed and the seeds are soft, like rice. You may use soy, nut, or oat milk instead of water, plus fresh or dried fruit, sweet herbs (i.e., mint, cinnamon, ginger), and a sweetener, to make a sweet hot cereal. To make them more nutty tasting, toast the seeds in a pan over medium until they pop, stirring very often, before adding the liquid.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Amaranth seeds are also an excellent included in grain dishes, upping the flavor and nutrition as part of a rice pilaf or stuffing. Try using 4 parts oats and 1 part toasted amaranth in your favorite oatmeal recipe, cooked along with raisins and fresh fruit.</cooking>
    <nutrition>Amaranth seeds provide vitamin A, K, B2, B6, C, and folate, as well as palmitic, oleic, and linoleic acids, plus the minerals calcium, iron, magnesium, phosphorus, potassium, zinc, copper, and manganese. They also provide a great amount of a more complete protein than that in of the true grains.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>The leaves are astringent. An infusion has been used as a gargle for hoarseness, as well as for diarrhea, excessive menstruation, and intestinal bleeding.</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes>1</hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Don't harvest amaranth if Hernándo Cortés is watching. He made amaranth illegal when he conquered the Aztec Indians, objecting to its use in human sacrifice (while in his native Spain, the Inquisition was burning people at the stake for religious crimes such as being Jewish), and incidentally weakening them through starvation, so he could steal their gold. The punishment for possession of this controlled substance was death!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Also, don't eat the leaves if you have kidney problems. Like spinach, amaranth leaves contain oxalic acid (in quantities harmless to healthy people).</cautions>
    <similarPlants>Because this is a large group of species, a number of other plants resemble them enough to cause confusion when they're all young, so you should wait until you see the distinctive large, dense seed spikes before harvesting amaranth for first time. You can always return for the leaves the following year, much easier to do if you're still alive!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Lamb's-quarters, also edible, is probably the most similar-looking plant, but it's leaves are diamond-shaped and toothed, and its seed spikes are comparatively sparse. Both plants are sometimes called pigweed, a confusing name better avoided!</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes>Black nightshade leaves are poisonous raw, and they get some people sick cooked too. The medium-sized leaves are downy or smooth, oval to heart-shaped, and deep green with wavy or coarsely toothed edges, not rough and coarse like amaranth's, but  similar enough to confuse beginners. But the flowers are completely different, and the fruit is a berry, so once either species flowers or goes to seed, you can easily tell the plants apart.</poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous>0</poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Pigweed</commonNames>
    <common>1</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive></invasive>
    <foodUses>
      <id>2589</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.76048300 1300001477</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:17</dateadded>
      <salad>1</salad>
      <potherb>1</potherb>
      <root>1</root>
      <nut></nut>
      <seed></seed>
      <seasoning></seasoning>
      <tea></tea>
      <fruitBerry></fruitBerry>
      <coffee></coffee>
      <flout></flout>
      <pickles></pickles>
      <other></other>
    </foodUses>
    <edibleParts>
      <id>2590</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.83311300 1300001477</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:17</dateadded>
      <leaves></leaves>
      <flower></flower>
      <root></root>
      <nut>1</nut>
      <seed>1</seed>
      <stem></stem>
      <fruitBerry></fruitBerry>
      <pod></pod>
      <bud>1</bud>
      <shoot></shoot>
      <twigs></twigs>
    </edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Don't use this plant when Hernándo Cortés is watching. Because of its use in ritual human sacrifice, and because eradicating a major food source made his conquest of Mexico easier, he'd have you executed if he caught you with it. It's a very tasty wild food, but not worth losing your head over!</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser></teaser>
    <primaryHabitats>
      <id>2592</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.98709700 1300001477</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:17</dateadded>
      <lawns></lawns>
      <fields></fields>
      <thickets></thickets>
      <woodlands></woodlands>
      <marshes></marshes>
      <swamps></swamps>
      <seashore></seashore>
      <disturbed></disturbed>
      <edgeHabitats></edgeHabitats>
      <trailAndRoadside></trailAndRoadside>
      <bogs></bogs>
      <riversLakes></riversLakes>
      <parks></parks>
      <cultiavedPlaces></cultiavedPlaces>
    </primaryHabitats>
    <habitats>
      <id>2591</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.90519200 1300001477</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:17</dateadded>
      <lawns></lawns>
      <fields></fields>
      <thickets></thickets>
      <woodlands></woodlands>
      <marshes></marshes>
      <swamps></swamps>
      <seashore></seashore>
      <disturbed></disturbed>
      <edgeHabitats></edgeHabitats>
      <trailAndRoadside></trailAndRoadside>
      <bogs></bogs>
      <riversLakes></riversLakes>
      <parks></parks>
      <cultiavedPlaces></cultiavedPlaces>
    </habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Lamb's-Quarters</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon></veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>6</id>
      <title>Amaranth Porridge</title>
      <slug>amaranth-porridge</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <directions>Here is an update version of the classic Scottish breakfast dish with the addition of berries that will make the three Bears so happy, they'll be willing to share their cereal with Goldilocks! Serve hot.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. grape seed oil or canola oil&lt;br /&gt;1 cup steel-cut oats&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup amaranth&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup lecithin granules&lt;br /&gt;4 cups soy-rice milk, nut milk, or other vegan milk&lt;br /&gt;2 tsp. clear liquid stevia (an herbal sweetener available in health food stores)&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. cinnamon, ground&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. vanilla extract&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. orange extract&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. almond extract&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. salt&lt;br /&gt;1 large green apple, chopped&lt;br /&gt;1-1/2 cups red mulberries or other berries&lt;br /&gt;2/3 cup raisins&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup lecithin granules (available in health food stores‚ (optional))&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup oat bran (optional)	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. In a saucepan, cook the oats and amaranth in the oil over medium heat 5 minutes, or until fragrant, stirring often.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Add all ingredients except the lecithin and bran, bring to a boil over medium heat, stirring constantly, reduce the heat to low and simmer, uncovered, 30 minutes, or until the porridge is thickened and soft, stirring occasionally.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Remove from the heat and let set, uncovered, 15 minutes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 6&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 15 minutes&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cooking and setting time: 45 minutes&lt;br /&gt;</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>7</id>
      <title>5)Amaranth Seeds</title>
      <slug>5amaranth-seeds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>After you blow away most of amaranth's chaff, you get large quantities of these tasty, nutritious, tiny, black, circular seeds.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/AmaranthSeeds.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>8</id>
      <title>4)Mature Common Amaranth</title>
      <slug>4mature-common-amaranth</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>Mature common amaranth has tall spikes, densely covered with flowers or seeds, and the oval, smooth-edged, alternate, long-stalked leaves.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T1338x1895-17206.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>9</id>
      <title>2)Mature Low Amaranth</title>
      <slug>2mature-low-amaranth</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>Note the irregular, alternate, elliptical, long-stalked, smooth-edged, notched leaves, and the spikes of tiny seeds. Here it creeps along the ground, but it can also be upright.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T2272x1256-15666.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>10</id>
      <title>1)Low Amaranth with Seed Spikes</title>
      <slug>1low-amaranth-with-seed-spikes</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>This amaranth species has uncharacteristically sparse seed spikes, but the leaves make a superb potherb. Here it's upright, but it can also creep along the ground.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/AmaranthDrawing.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>11</id>
      <title>3)Common Amaranth Seed Heads</title>
      <slug>3common-amaranth-seed-heads</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>The hundreds of tiny, bristly looking bracts on these upright spikes hold thousands of delicious seeds.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T418x601-17202.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>12</id>
    <title>Chicory</title>
    <slug>chicory</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Cichorium intybus&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family &lt;i&gt;Asteraceae  (Compositae)&lt;/i&gt;, the astor or composite family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>13</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.36028300 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>14</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.37445200 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>15</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.38900100 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>Leaves: Early spring and late fall, plus winter if mild&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Flowers: Late spring to early fall&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Taproot (for making coffee): Early spring to late fall (and winter in mild climates)</season>
    <habitat>Chicory needs full sunlight and well-drained soil, and thrives in disturbed habitats, roadsides, fields, and parks.</habitat>
    <range>Throughout most of the continental US and Canada</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>In cold-weather seasons, look for basal rosettes of jagged, dandelion-like leaves with teeth pointing outward, and reddish midribs. In the summer, look for nearly leafless stems around four feet tall, with showy, sky-blue composite flowers consisting of fringed ray flowers and no disk flowers.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>Chicory forms a basal rosette very early in the spring, with leaves three to ten inches long. They begin lance-shaped, with small teeth that soon become quite large, like dandelion's, but often pointing outward, not always toward the leaf's base. Chicory's leaf's midrib, usually tinged red, has some hair.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A zigzag flower stalk 1.5 to four feet tall (sometimes taller) with tiny, barely noticeable, alternate, lance-shaped, stalkless, toothed leaves comes up in the summer (its woody skeleton persists through winter), bearing 15 to 20 showy, blue, stalked, composite flower heads with fringed ray flowers, but no disk flowers, and many stamens ending in the letter "Y." The tiny, inconspicuous seeds that follow blow away in the wind.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Chicory usually grows in dense stands. The whole plant exudes a white, milky latex when cut. Its deep, stiff, beige, perennial taproot usually grows much longer than a carrot's.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>• Basal rosette of deeply toothed leaves&lt;br /&gt;•Some of the teeth pointing outward&lt;br /&gt;• Often reddish midrib in the basal leaves&lt;br /&gt;• Some fine hairs on the midrib&lt;br /&gt;• Zigzag, nearly bare stem, up to four feet tall, with very small, alternate, toothed, lance-shaped leaves&lt;br /&gt;• Blue composite flowers with fringe-tipped rays, mostly during the summer&lt;br /&gt;• Deep, stiff taproot&lt;br /&gt;• Woody remnants of a flower stalk connected to many of the rosettes in early spring and fall&lt;br /&gt;• White, milky sap wherever the plant is broken&lt;br /&gt;</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Collect the leaves of the smallest basal rosettes before the teeth get large and the leaves become too bitter to be palatable, in very early spring, and again when new growth appears in late fall. Pass a sharp knife under the rosette to sever it from the taproot—much more efficient that picking off the leaves a few at a time. Shake off the rosette to get rid of as much debris as possible.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You can also dig up the root for making coffee any time of year with a shovel—much easier than using a trowel. Do so after it's rained, when the soil is more yielding, and choose a location that isn't rocky.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I don't find the flowers particularly tasty, although some people do eat them.</harvesting>
    <cooking>Chicory leaves have a robust, dandelion-lettuce flavor, with a hint of bitterness that must be managed wisely. Use the leaves like dandelion leaves. Add the young leaves sparingly to salads or sandwiches. Too many may create too much bitterness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Or sautée them in olive (or other) oil with herbs and spices, then add a sauce consistent with a culinary tradition that uses the same spices (i.e., Mexican spices + salsa) and simmer. Leaves shrink when you sautée them, concentrating the bitterness, but this method counteracts that tendency. Adding the sautéed greens to soups or stews, i.e., ones containing beans or noodles, [-also] works well.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The roots are usually too tough and woody to eat (although you can still cook them, after which they'll taste like cooked wood!), but you can chop them, then roast at 350 degrees for an hour or until blackened, stirring occasionally, chop further to the size of coffee in a blender or coffee or spice grinder, and brew into a well-known caffeine-free coffee substitute. This works, although I prefer the seeds of the Kentucky coffee-tree, which makes a better wild coffee substitute.</cooking>
    <nutrition>The leaves are an excellent source of calcium, and they also provide some potassium, phosphorus, copper, zinc, magnesium, and vitamins A, K, C, E, plus some B-complex vitamins.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>Like its relative, the dandelion, which has superseded it in modern herbal practice, a decoction of the root has been used for various liver problems, and to aid digestion.</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions></cautions>
    <similarPlants>Commercial chicory, which doesn't grow wild in the US, is actually a different species, &lt;i&gt;C. endivia&lt;/i&gt;, also called curly endive.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When they're very young, dandelion rosettes, also edible, resemble chicory rosettes, but dandelions' basal leaves' teeth always point toward the leaf's base. Some of chicory's leaves' teeth point outward. Chicory's basal leaves' midribs are often tinged reddish, with some fine hairs, qualities dandelions lack. Many chicory rosettes have remnants of the previous year's woody flower stalks, which dandelions also lack. And when they flower, the dandelion remains a basal rosette and produces its familiar yellow flowers, while chicory grows a tall stem with many blue flowers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Young wild lettuce rosettes resemble chicory rosettes, but wild lettuce has fibrous roots, never a taproot, and it's midrib is triangular in cross-section. Later on, its flowers are yellow, like dandelions'.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Blue Sailors, Succory, Coffeeweed and Cornflower</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses>
      <id>2581</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.60706800 1300001476</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:16</dateadded>
      <salad></salad>
      <potherb></potherb>
      <root></root>
      <nut></nut>
      <seed></seed>
      <seasoning></seasoning>
      <tea></tea>
      <fruitBerry></fruitBerry>
      <coffee></coffee>
      <flout></flout>
      <pickles></pickles>
      <other></other>
    </foodUses>
    <edibleParts>
      <id>2582</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.67803400 1300001476</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:16</dateadded>
      <leaves></leaves>
      <flower></flower>
      <root></root>
      <nut></nut>
      <seed></seed>
      <stem></stem>
      <fruitBerry></fruitBerry>
      <pod></pod>
      <bud></bud>
      <shoot></shoot>
      <twigs></twigs>
    </edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>This very common, widespread plant, similar to the related dandelion when young, has sky-blue composite flowers that make the plant easy to spot when it dominates roadsides in the summer.&lt;br /&gt;</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser></teaser>
    <primaryHabitats>
      <id>2584</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.84793600 1300001476</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:16</dateadded>
      <lawns></lawns>
      <fields></fields>
      <thickets></thickets>
      <woodlands></woodlands>
      <marshes></marshes>
      <swamps></swamps>
      <seashore></seashore>
      <disturbed></disturbed>
      <edgeHabitats></edgeHabitats>
      <trailAndRoadside></trailAndRoadside>
      <bogs></bogs>
      <riversLakes></riversLakes>
      <parks></parks>
      <cultiavedPlaces></cultiavedPlaces>
    </primaryHabitats>
    <habitats>
      <id>2583</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.75189900 1300001476</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:16</dateadded>
      <lawns></lawns>
      <fields></fields>
      <thickets></thickets>
      <woodlands></woodlands>
      <marshes></marshes>
      <swamps></swamps>
      <seashore></seashore>
      <disturbed></disturbed>
      <edgeHabitats></edgeHabitats>
      <trailAndRoadside></trailAndRoadside>
      <bogs></bogs>
      <riversLakes></riversLakes>
      <parks></parks>
      <cultiavedPlaces></cultiavedPlaces>
    </habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Common Dandelion, Wild Lettuce</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>16</id>
      <title>Savory Chicory with Sweet Red Dal</title>
      <slug>savory-chicory-with-sweet-red-dal</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <directions>Here’s a quick, delicious way to prepare these healthful tiny red lentils, where savory chicory with creamy pignoli nuts and sweet spices make the dish special.&lt;br /&gt;	&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. corn oil&lt;br /&gt;2 cups very young chicory leaves, chopped&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. cardamom&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. cloves, ground&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. cinnamon, ground&lt;br /&gt;3 cups soy-rice milk, oat milk, or nut milk&lt;br /&gt;1 cup red dal&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup commercial currants&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup pignoli nuts&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. fresh orange rind&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. salt	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Sautée the chicory in the corn oil with the cardamom, cloves, and cinnamon 10 minutes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Transfer to a saucepan with all the remaining ingredients except the salt, bring to a boil over medium heat, reduce the heat to low, cover, and simmer for 35 minutes or until the lentils are tender.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Stir in the salt at the end to prevent the beans from staying hard.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 4 to 6&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 45 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>17</id>
      <title>1)Chicory Young Basal Rosette and Taproot</title>
      <slug>1chicory-young-basal-rosette-and-taproot</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>These young, toothed leaves, before the lobes develop and they become bitter, are the best to eat. Note the very long taproot, and the remnant of last year's flower stalk—good field characteristics for identifying the young plant, and differentiating it from wild lettuce and dandelions respectively.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T2018x2675-17113.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>18</id>
      <title>2)Chicory Young Basal Rosette</title>
      <slug>2chicory-young-basal-rosette</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>[-The]A basal rosette with toothed leaves, where the underside of the midrib of one of the center leaves is tinged with red, plus the woody remnant of last year's flower stalk, characterize chicory in early spring. This stage, before the leaves develop lobes, is when you want to cut off the top of the roots and collect the rosettes.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T3072x2304-19619.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>19</id>
      <title>4)Chicory Stand in Flower</title>
      <slug>4chicory-stand-in-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>The nearly leafless flower stalks with short, zigzag branches, and the showy, blue, composite flowers, bloom along roadsides and disturbed soil throughout the country throughout the summer.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J944x2164-21017.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>20</id>
      <title>5)Chicory Flower</title>
      <slug>5chicory-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>Chicory's blue composite flowers consist of many petal-like ray flowers, each fringed with five jagged points at the tips. The many stamens look like upside-down scissors tucked into a sheath.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1484x1420-21015.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>21</id>
      <title>3)Chicory Large Rosette</title>
      <slug>3chicory-large-rosette</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>By the time chicory's basal leaves develop lobes, they're already very bitter-tasting.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1602x1308-21012.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>22</id>
    <title>Burdock</title>
    <slug>burdock</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Arctium minus&lt;/i&gt;, common burdock; and &lt;i&gt;A. lappa&lt;/i&gt;, greater burdock</scientificName>
    <group>Family:&lt;i&gt; Asteraceae&lt;/i&gt;, Aster family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>23</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.56225800 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <annual></annual>
      <biennial>1</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous></perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine></vine>
      <shrub></shrub>
      <tree></tree>
      <seaweed></seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>24</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.57182100 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>25</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.58682300 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>1. Taproot of 1st year plant: spring, summer, and fall&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Taproot of 2nd year plant: spring, before the flower stalk appears&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Stem: mid-spring&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;4. Leaf stalks of greater burdock: spring, summer, and fall</season>
    <habitat>Burdock grows in the sun or partial shade, in disturbed soil, backyards, untended gardens, empty lots, overgrown fields, meadows, edge habitats, and urban parks.</habitat>
    <range>Burdock grows across most of North America, except for the deep south.</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Eurasia</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for the basal rosettes of large, coarse, wedge-shaped leaves which are whitish underneath. It's tall stems bear purple, shaving brush-shaped flowers and brown, prickly burrs.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This is a delicious root vegetable, prized in east Asia, with the bonus of an edible immature stem, which is prized in Italy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This coarse-looking biennial has huge, wedge-shaped leaves up to two feet long and one foot broad, forming a basal rosette the first year and at the beginning of the second year. Unlike similar plants, the leaves are whitish and finely wooly underneath.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The purplish-green leafstalks can grow up to 1.5 feet long and .75 inch thick. Common burdock's leaf stalks are hollow, not furrowed. Greater burdock's leaf stalks are solid, with a groove along the upper surface.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The long, deep, stout taproot, whitish after being scrubbed, consists of an outer rind and inner core. It can grow up to four feet long and three inches wide, and smells like potatoes and dirt.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The erect stem, which arises from the center of the basal rosette in mid-spring of the second year, grows from two to five feet tall in common burdock and up to nine feet tall in greater burdock. Its alternate leaves are similar to the basal leaves, but smaller, especially toward the top.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Arising from green bases, the bristly, purple-pink, spherical, composite flowers, short-stemmed and 0.75 inch across in common burdock, long-stemmed and one to 1.5 inches across in greater burdock, resemble shaving brushes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The ripe fruits, the inspiration for Velcro, consist of spherical burrs the size of the flowers, covered with tiny hooks. They stick to virtually anything they touch. Inside are many small, hard, curved, brown seeds.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Basal rosette of wedge-shaped, long-stalked, very large leaves&lt;br /&gt;•Leaves finely wooly and whitish underneath, alternate on the stem&lt;br /&gt;•Long taproot that's whitish when scrubbed, consisting of an outer rind and inner core.&lt;br /&gt;•Flower stalk two to nine feet tall&lt;br /&gt;•Purple, shaving brush-like flowers giving way to ovate, brown burrs bearing tiny hooks&lt;br /&gt;•Many small, hard, curved, brown seeds inside brown burrs</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Burdock's taproot is very deep. There are three things you need to make this job relatively easy:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. A shovel&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. A location where burdock is growing that's relatively free of rocks (not hard to find, since burdock is so common)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Moist soil, from a period when there's been plenty of rain, not when it hasn't rained for weeks and the soil is rock hard&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Place the shovel an inch from the center of the rosette. Aim straight down, so you don't cut through the root. Grip the handle firmly with both hands. Repeatedly stomp on the shovel as hard as you can, to drive it all the way into the earth. Now, you can chance pushing upward with the shovel while gently pulling the leaves, and you may unearth the root, or most of the root, with no further effort. If it's unyielding, don't yank off the leaves, but remove the clod of soil with the shovel and repeat the process on the other side of the plant. When you're done, refill the hole with soil, so you'll create no environmental impact.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cut off the stem with a pocket knife or pruning shears soon after it appears in mid-spring, when it's large, but still very soft and flexible, long before the flowers appear.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cut off the leafstalks with a pocket knife any time during the growing season, but only use greater burdock. There's not enough food in common burdock's leafstalks to make it worthwhile.</harvesting>
    <cooking>The taproot tastes like a combination of potatoes and artichokes. Scrub it with a metal scouring pad under running water to clean it. Slice diagonally, razor thin, or use the finest slicing blade of a food processor, so the root becomes tender more quickly.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Some foraging writers who don't cook suggest peeling the root, because the Japanese do so. But that's only because they prefer the whiter color of core to the darker one of the rind, which is just as tasty as the core. Digging up burdock takes quite a bit of effort, so you're not going to want to throw out half your harvest unnecessarily!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Burdock root is best simmered or steamed 15 to 20 minutes, or until tender, i.e., in soups, stews or casseroles. You can sauté it first if desired, but cooking it in liquid is necessary to tenderize it. You can also bake it in a covered baking dish that includes at least a little liquid, so the hot steam tenderizes it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While not poisonous raw, it's hard to digest, and members of traditional cultures cooked it, even in the days where going out to gather firewood could be dangerous because, over the years, they determined that it had the best food value cooked.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Peel the fibers from the stems and flower stalks. This can stain your hands brown, so you may want to wear rubber gloves. Slice, then parboil 1 minute to remove the bitterness. Add it in any vegetable dish and 5 to 15 more minutes. It tastes like artichoke hearts.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The leaves are so bitter, if you squeeze one and touch your finger to your tongue, you'll wish you hadn't! Some people boil the very young leaves in multiple changes of water to get rid of the bitterness, but there are so many superior wild greens, you'd make much better use of your time and effort by learning them!</cooking>
    <nutrition>Burdock root provides vitamins B6 and C, magnesium, phosphorus, potassium, manganese, and sodium. It's an excellent source of inulin, a polysaccharide that doesn't get absorbed or elicit an insulin response, and is beneficial to people with blood sugar problems.&lt;br /&gt;</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>A decoction made by boiling the root has been used for centuries in Europe and Asia as a blood purifier (detoxifier in modern parlance), and for the skin, liver, and kidneys.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A poultice made by mixing the chopped leaves with clay and water, and bandaged to bruises, clears the the bruises in a few days. Mixing them with spearmint stems and clay may make this even more effective.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Burn care workers have reputedly had success applying the leaves topically to inhibit bacterial growth, speed healing time, and ease the changing of dressings.</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes>1</hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Don't eat the seeds, which may be poisonous (and they're too hard to eat anyway). And the burrs may actually be fatal—by the time you remove all the itchy fragments from your clothing, you could die of old age!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And don't eat the leaves if you're an African gray parrot—they'll get stuck in your digestive tract and kill you.</cautions>
    <similarPlants>"Dock" means deduct or remove, and unrelated plants that people remove from their gardens, such as the unrelated curly dock, a.k.a. yellow dock (&lt;i&gt;Rumex crispus&lt;/i&gt;), which has edible leaves and stems, have the same confusing last name. But curly dock has narrow leaves, not white underneath, with curled edges, a hard, yellow taproot, and different flowers and seeds.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Curly dock's relative bitter dock or broadleaf dock (&lt;i&gt;R. obtusifolia&lt;/i&gt;) has large leaves that do resemble burdock's, and the plants sometimes grow side-by-side, but as a relative of yellow dock, bitter dock's hard, inedible taproot is bright yellow when scraped, and again the leaves don't have burdock's white, whooly fuzz underneath. Although nonpoisonous, all parts of this plant usually taste so bad that eating them will make you wish you were dead!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cardoon (&lt;i&gt;Cynara cardunculus&lt;/i&gt;) is an edible European relative of burdock that doesn't grow wild in the US. Italians in the US use the peeled, parboiled immature stem of burdock in the spring the same way cardoons are used in Italy, and, because they don't know burdock's correct English name, they incorrectly call it cardoon too, creating both confusion and some delicious recipes.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes>Cocklebur (&lt;i&gt;Xanthium spp.&lt;/i&gt;) has burrs too, but they're arranged spirally, the rest of the plant doesn't look like burdock, you don't eat burdock when it has burrs, and I doubt anyone has ever been poisoned confusing the two, but you should be aware of the possibility of confusion.</poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart>1</poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Love Leaves, Beggar's Buttons, Cockle Buttons, Harebur, Gobo, Thorny Bur</commonNames>
    <common>1</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses>
      <id>2585</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.18570600 1300001477</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:17</dateadded>
      <salad></salad>
      <potherb></potherb>
      <root></root>
      <nut></nut>
      <seed></seed>
      <seasoning></seasoning>
      <tea></tea>
      <fruitBerry></fruitBerry>
      <coffee></coffee>
      <flout></flout>
      <pickles></pickles>
      <other></other>
    </foodUses>
    <edibleParts>
      <id>2586</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.25829500 1300001477</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:17</dateadded>
      <leaves></leaves>
      <flower></flower>
      <root></root>
      <nut></nut>
      <seed></seed>
      <stem></stem>
      <fruitBerry></fruitBerry>
      <pod></pod>
      <bud></bud>
      <shoot></shoot>
      <twigs></twigs>
    </edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Burdock provides a delicious, very deep taproot that comes from Asia. When you try to harvest it, you'll soon realize there's a hungry Asian person on the other end trying to do the same thing! </flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser></teaser>
    <primaryHabitats>
      <id>2588</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.42043200 1300001477</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:17</dateadded>
      <lawns></lawns>
      <fields></fields>
      <thickets></thickets>
      <woodlands></woodlands>
      <marshes></marshes>
      <swamps></swamps>
      <seashore></seashore>
      <disturbed></disturbed>
      <edgeHabitats></edgeHabitats>
      <trailAndRoadside></trailAndRoadside>
      <bogs></bogs>
      <riversLakes></riversLakes>
      <parks></parks>
      <cultiavedPlaces></cultiavedPlaces>
    </primaryHabitats>
    <habitats>
      <id>2587</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.33145200 1300001477</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:17</dateadded>
      <lawns></lawns>
      <fields></fields>
      <thickets></thickets>
      <woodlands></woodlands>
      <marshes></marshes>
      <swamps></swamps>
      <seashore></seashore>
      <disturbed></disturbed>
      <edgeHabitats></edgeHabitats>
      <trailAndRoadside></trailAndRoadside>
      <bogs></bogs>
      <riversLakes></riversLakes>
      <parks></parks>
      <cultiavedPlaces></cultiavedPlaces>
    </habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride>1</wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Curly Dock, Bitter Dock</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated>Cocklebur</poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon></veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>26</id>
      <title>1)Vegan Garlic Butter</title>
      <slug>1vegan-garlic-butter</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <directions>Here’s a savory French garlic butter-style spread based on miso, lecithin, and olive oil instead of animal fat, that will flavor bread (it's especially good on bread you're going to toast), pasta, vegetables, soups, or any dish that calls for seasoned butter. With the addition of a small amount of olive oil, it's also great for sautéeing.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3 tbs. wild garlic or 6 cloves of commercial garlic&lt;br /&gt;2/3 cup fresh parsley&lt;br /&gt;1 cup mellow (light-colored) miso (available in health food stores)&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup olive oil&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup lecithin granules (available in health food stores)&lt;br /&gt;2 tsp. rosemary, ground&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. marjoram, ground&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. sage, ground&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. chili paste or hot sauce&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. turmeric	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Chop the garlic and parsley in a food processor.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Add the remaining ingredients and purée.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Makes 1-3/4 cups&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 5 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <recipe>
      <id>27</id>
      <title>2)Baked Burdock Root</title>
      <slug>2baked-burdock-root</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <directions>Here’s an irresistible wild snack food you’ll nibble on until the last bit is gone!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;4 cups burdock root, thinly sliced&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup Vegan Garlic Butter&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. Vege-sal (available in health food stores)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. water&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. lemon juice	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mix all ingredients together and bake, covered, in an oiled casserole dish, 45 minutes, or until the water has evaporated and the roots are lightly browned.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 5 minutes&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Baking time: 45 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>28</id>
      <title>1)Common Burdock Basal Rosette and Taproot</title>
      <slug>1common-burdock-basal-rosette-and-taproot</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>The large, coarse, long-stalked, wedge-shaped leaves, with their whitish undersides, reveal the whereabouts of the large, deep taproot, which is white after being scrubbed.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/BurdockDrawing1.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>29</id>
      <title>3)Common Burdock Flower Stalk</title>
      <slug>3common-burdock-flower-stalk</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>This is the stage where the immature central flower stalk is delicious peeled, parboiled, and prepared like artichoke hearts.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/BurdockImmatureFlowerStalk.3.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>30</id>
      <title>4)Burdock Flower</title>
      <slug>4burdock-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>The spherical composite flower consists of many tiny flowers bunched together like a purple shaving brush, set above a round, green, prickly base.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T1272x1448-15763.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>31</id>
      <title>5)Burdock Burrs</title>
      <slug>5burdock-burrs</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>These annoying, spherical, light brown burrs grow on long, branching, terminal stalks. Their hooked tips let them stick to clothing and fur, and they're full of seeds, accounting for this Eurasian invader's spread through North America.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1536x2020-20946.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>32</id>
      <title>6)Burdock Seeds</title>
      <slug>6burdock-seeds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>The small, hard, brown, curved, possibly poisonous seeds are good to throw into your neighbor's garden. Next year, you can help him or her get rid of the ensuing "weeds," which you'll get to eat!</caption>
      <poisonous>0</poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T483x570-16823.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>33</id>
    <title>Chickweed</title>
    <slug>chickweed</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Stellaria media&lt;/i&gt;, common chickweed, and &lt;i&gt;S. pubera,&lt;/i&gt; star chickweed </scientificName>
    <group>&lt;i&gt;Caryophyllaceae&lt;/i&gt;, the pink family or carnation family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>34</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.81187100 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <annual>1</annual>
      <biennial></biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous></perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine></vine>
      <shrub></shrub>
      <tree></tree>
      <seaweed></seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>35</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.82197800 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear>1</allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>36</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.83762100 1291972536</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>Chickweed is in season all year, even growing in the winter any time it's above freezing, but it's at its best in early spring and mid- to late fall.&lt;br /&gt;</season>
    <habitat>Chickweed grows in lawns, meadows, gardens, and disturbed areas, in full sunlight and partial shade. In very cold weather, look for it along sun-heated walls with southern exposure, where it thrives in the milder microhabitat.</habitat>
    <range>Various chickweed species grow throughout North America</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for mats of slender-stemmed, small plants with opposite leaves and star-like, white flowers. Chickweed grows where there's at least some sun, even during the colder seasons when few other greens are around.&lt;br /&gt;</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This small, sprawling annual's slender stem bears a distinctive row of fine white hairs, and tiny, smooth-edged, spade-shaped to oval, opposite leaves. Unlike some other ground-hugging plants, it never forms a basal rosette. Common chickweed's leaves have short leaf stalks, while star chickweed has stalkless leaves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Tiny, white flowers grow at the tips of the plants, with five petals so deeply split that they look like ten. Five green sepals surround the petals.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Tiny yellow-brown, oval-shaped seeds fall out of tiny ovate, stalked capsules before the plant dies.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Mats of slender-stemmed plants growing close to the ground&lt;br /&gt;•A thin line of tiny, white hairs along the stem&lt;br /&gt;•Tiny, opposite, toothless leaves&lt;br /&gt;•No colored sap&lt;br /&gt;•Tiny white flowers&lt;br /&gt;•Five white petals each split into a "V"-shape that makes them look like ten petals&lt;br /&gt;•Five green sepals</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Look around for where this plant is the most plentiful before collecting. One spot can have some chickweed mixed with grass, which you'll need to separate out, whereas other places may have dense mats of pure chickweed. And collect where it's thriving, young and bright green, before it begins to go to seed, becomes light green, and gets stringy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Grab and bag the entire plant, avoiding any with yellowed leaves or discolored stems, or clip with shears, a knife, or scissors.</harvesting>
    <cooking>The whole plant, except the roots, is delicious—raw it tastes like corn-on-the-cob, or like cornsilk, cooked it's more like spinach. Always chop the entire plant, except the roots, into bite-sized pieces before using it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A salad vegetable and potherb par excellence, it's also great in sandwiches, used like sprouts or in mid-Eastern recipes, with hummus in pita bread. It's wonderful steamed, or added to soups, stews, and casseroles. You can also sautée it. It cooks in about 5 minutes, be careful not to overcook.</cooking>
    <nutrition>Chickweed is a nutritional powerhouse, providing vitamins C, A, D,  folic acid, riboflavin, niacin, and thiamine, as well as the minerals calcium, magnesium, potassium, manganese, zinc, iron, phosphorus, sodium, copper, silica.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>Chickweed been applied topically to various skin sores and irritations for hundreds of years (you'd think after all that time, the sores would finally heal!)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Back in the day, while doctors were bleeding their patients, sometimes to death (that's how they finally got rid of George Washington's stubborn cold!), herbalists gave chickweed to convalescents after serious illnesses to rebuild their strength before opportunistic infections could cause a relapse. Turns out chickweed is loaded with more vitamins and minerals than a health food store, so it probably replaced the nutrients the immune system needs, which had been depleted during the illness.&lt;br /&gt;</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes>1</hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions></cautions>
    <similarPlants>Other less common species of chickweed, also edible, grow throughout the North America. Mouse-ear chickweed (&lt;i&gt;Cerastium vulgatum&lt;/i&gt;), also with opposite leaves, is hairy all over. It's good cooked, but you won't enjoy it raw unless you like eating hairy food!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Doorweed (&lt;i&gt;Polygonum aviculture&lt;/i&gt;) looks a little like chickweed because it grows along the ground, sometimes along with chickweed, but its leaves are alternate, not opposite. Unlike chickweed, it grows in a basal rosette. And  there's no row of hair on the stems. Instead, the stems are punctuated by joints. The plant isn't poisonous, but with the texture of string, it's not edible.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes>Prostrate spurge (&lt;i&gt;Euphorbia supina&lt;/i&gt;) and spotted spurge (&lt;i&gt;E. maculata&lt;/i&gt;), which grow close to the ground and have opposite leaves, look a little like chickweed, and they can grow side-by-side with chickweed. But spurge exudes an acrid, white, milky sap when cut. Chickweed doesn't. Spurge lacks chickweed's row of tiny white hairs growing along the stem, and it grows in rosettes rather than forming mats. Spurge, which contains diterpene esters, causes nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea when eaten, or redness, swelling, blisters after contact with the skin and exposure to sunlight.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Scarlet pimpernel (&lt;i&gt;Anagallis arvensis&lt;/i&gt;) is a small plant with opposite leaves that grows along the ground, but it lacks chickweed's row of fine hairs on the stem, and it has a scarlet flower. It contains a triterpenoid saponin and a glycoside (cyclamine) that cause constipation, skin inflammation, staggering, headache, kidney problems, and nausea.</poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Chickenwort, Craches, Maruns, Winterweed</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>0</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Chickweed gets its name because chickens love it, so you should eat it even if you're afraid to (that would make you a chicken, and you'll still love it!)</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Doorweed</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated>Spotted Spurge, Scarlet Pimpernel</poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>37</id>
      <title>Garlicky Chickweed with Penne</title>
      <slug>garlicky-chickweed-with-penne</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <directions>Here’s a fast and tasty recipe where chickweed’s robust flavor holds its own with the garlic. Along with the other seasonings, these two primary flavors add a savory element to the more mild-flavored pasta.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3 cups penne pasta&lt;br /&gt;2 cloves of garlic, chopped&lt;br /&gt;8 cups chickweed, chopped&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. corn oil&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. marjoram, ground&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. black pepper, ground&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1 tbs. tamari soy sauce (available in health food stores) or soy sauce, or to taste	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Cook the penne in boiling, salted water with a dash of olive oil according to the manufacturer’s directions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Meanwhile, sautée the garlic in the corn oil 5 minutes, or until very lightly browned. Take care not to burn the garlic, which is very easy to do, and would ruin the dish.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Stir in the pasta and other remaining ingredients, reduce the heat to low, cover, and cook 5 minutes, or until the chickweed is just wilted.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 4 to 6&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 20 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>38</id>
      <title>1)Star Chickweed</title>
      <slug>1star-chickweed</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>The stalkless opposite leaves, tiny, white, split petals, and stalked seed pods, plus the slender stem, characterize this easy-to-recognize plant.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/StarChickweedPainting.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>39</id>
      <title>2)Common Chickweed</title>
      <slug>2common-chickweed</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>The opposite, smooth-edges, stalked, spade-shaped leaves, and the row of white hairs along the stem make this species easy to ID, even without flowers.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Star Chickweed1.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>40</id>
      <title>3)Star Chickweed Flowers</title>
      <slug>3star-chickweed-flowers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>The five white petals of these alphabetic flowers, set inside five green sepals, are split so deeply, each looks like the letter "V," while the single pistil spreads out into a letter "Y," to catch the pollen made on the tiny, pink-tipped stamens. </caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T463x484-18906.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>41</id>
      <title>4)Mouse-ear Chickweed</title>
      <slug>4mouse-ear-chickweed</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:36</dateadded>
      <caption>With opposite leaves and five deeply split petals, this species is similar to star and common chickweed, except that it's hairy all over. It's edible, but you have to cook it.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/MouseEarChickweedSide.2.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>44</id>
    <title>Common Plantain</title>
    <slug>common-plantain</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Plantago major&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family &lt;i&gt;Plantaginaceae&lt;/i&gt;, the plantain family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>45</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.05671000 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>46</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.07306900 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>47</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.08825300 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>The leaves are only edible when they first come up, in early spring, although a few young leaves you can eat still grow in the center of the basal rosettes well into summer. The seed capsules are edible from late spring through mid-summer, and the seeds themselves, if you can gather enough to make your effort worthwhile, ripen in late summer.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You can use the leaves medicinally spring, summer, and fall.</season>
    <habitat>This plant grows in sunny areas, partial shade, cultivated areas, lawns, meadows, parks, gardens, and fields, and on bare ground.</habitat>
    <range>Throughout North America, and virtually worldwide.</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for basal rosettes of oval, ribbed leaves and pencil-shaped spikes of green flowers on lawns, and in sunny, grassy areas.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This common herb has minimal value as food, but it's among the most important medicinal plants you can find in the field.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The oval leaves, which grow up to six inches long and four inches wide, form basal rosettes exclusively. Their ribbed appearance, created by parallel veins, makes them easy to recognize, as do the short, flattened, purple leaf stalks.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The green, inconspicuous, wind-pollinated, pencil-shaped, leafless flower spike, with protruding white stamens, grows six to eight inches tall, and blooms in the summer and fall. Inconspicuous, small, green, oblong fruits split open in late summer and fall to release tiny, black seeds.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The roots are fibrous.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Basal rosettes of oval, ribbed leaves&lt;br /&gt;•Short, flattened, purple leaf stalk&lt;br /&gt;•Green, inconspicuous, pencil-shaped flowers&lt;br /&gt;•Fibrous roots</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Pull off the leaves or flowers with your hand, or cut with a knife, and strip the immature, green fruits from the fruit stalk with your fingers.</harvesting>
    <cooking>This is one of the worst edible plants to use for food. Although you could eat the young leaves when they first appear in early spring, they're rather tough, and taste like wheat grass juice—a flavor few people love. The smaller leaves toward the center of the rosette that you can collect later on aren't any better.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I've coated the leaves with olive oil, miso, and spices, and roasted them in a hot oven, as people sometimes do with kale, turning them often to prevent burning. They sometimes taste good this way, but other times there's an unpleasant, bitter aftertaste.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The green, immature fruits taste like inferior peanuts—edible, not worth the trouble. And the seeds inside the mature fruits, which you can use to thicken drinks, the way people use related psyllium seeds and flax seeds, are so tiny, it's only on rare occasions where you'll find enough to be worth gathering.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There's only one really good thing I can say about using common plantain as food. It's not quite as bad as its relative, long-leaf plantain!</cooking>
    <nutrition>Common plantain contains vitamins C and K, plus the minerals calcium, potassium, and sulfur, as well as trace minerals. The seeds are a good source of vitamin B1.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>In contrast to its low value as food, this is one of the best herbs for skin irritations, and it's been used as such since prehistoric times. Mash some leaves until they produce juice (some people chew them) and repeatedly apply this to a mosquito bite right after you've been bitten. It will cure the bite in about 15 minutes if used promptly. It lessens the effects of bee stings, it's good for scrapes, cooking burns, cuts, and poison ivy rash, with anti-inflammatory substances and chemicals that stop bleeding. It also contains allantoin, which promotes cell proliferation and healing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A tea of the mucilagenous seeds acts as a bulk laxative, good for constipation, and to for relieving intestinal irritation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions></cautions>
    <similarPlants>The closely related long-leaf plantain (&lt;i&gt;P. lanceolata&lt;/i&gt;) has narrow, ribbed leaves, and a pineapple-shaped flower atop a sender, leafless flower stalk. You can use its leaves the same way as common plantain.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The word "plantain" refers to the foot-like shape of this plant's leaf, but it's unrelated to the banana-like plantain.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Broadleaf Plantain, Broad-leaved Plantain, Roadweed, Roundleaf Plantain, Cart Track Plant, Dooryard Plantain, Greater Plantago, Healing Blade, Hen Plant, Lamb's Foot, Snakeroot, Waybread, Wayside Plantain, White Man's Foot Print</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>A man used this plant to stop his brother's cut from bleeding. They were so impressed, Johnson and Johnson were inspired to invent the band-aide!&lt;br /&gt;</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated></similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <plantImage>
      <id>48</id>
      <title>1)Young Common Plantain Basal Rosette and Roots</title>
      <slug>1young-common-plantain-basal-rosette-and-roots</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>All the oval, ribbed leaves arise from the fibrous roots. At this stage, while the leaves aren't fully developed, they're at their best (or should I say, least worst!) to eat.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T992x879-19487.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>49</id>
      <title>2)Common Plantain Young Basal Rosette</title>
      <slug>2common-plantain-young-basal-rosette</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>If you're going to eat common plantain's leaves, this is the stage where they're at their most edible, before they become fully grown and too tough.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1540x1500-21086.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>50</id>
      <title>3)Common Plantain in Flower</title>
      <slug>3common-plantain-in-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The oval, ribbed leaves, in basal rosettes only, with their inconspicuous flowers that are shaped like green pencils, make the plant easy to identify. At this stage, the leaves taste like old shoes. [-You can cook them, and they'll taste like cooked old shoes! However, they're one of the most effective herbal medicines for skin irritations. Mash and apply for quick relief.]</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T1530x1950-16940.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>51</id>
      <title>4)Common Plantain Flower</title>
      <slug>4common-plantain-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>Easy to overlook, the green flower spikes are covered with protruding stamens.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T381x2272-16939.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>52</id>
    <title>Long-leaf Plantain</title>
    <slug>long-leaf-plantain</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Plantago lanceolata&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family &lt;i&gt;Plantaginaceae&lt;/i&gt;, plantain family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>53</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.22670400 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>54</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.24119300 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>55</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.25664400 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>The greatest number of tender, young leaves come up very early in the spring, although a few continue to grow in the center of the rosette through late fall.</season>
    <habitat>This plant grows in sunny areas, partial shade, cultivated areas, lawns, meadows, parks, gardens, and fields, and on bare ground.</habitat>
    <range>This European plants grows across the US and Canada, and virtually worldwide.</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for basal rosettes of lance-shaped, ribbed leaves and a smooth, slender, unbranched stem topped with a small, inconspicuous, pineapple-shaped flower, growing in great quantity on lawns and in sunny, grassy, and disturbed areas.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This common herb has minimal value as food, but it's important medicinally.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The lance-shaped leaves, which grow six to 12 inches long, form basal rosettes exclusively. Their ribbed appearance, created by three or five parallel veins, makes them easy to recognize.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A smooth, slender, unbranched stem growing less than one foot high supports a small, inconspicuous, cylindrical to pineapple-shaped brownish flower, with protruding white stamens. It blooms from late spring to early fall.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The roots are fibrous.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Basal rosettes of lance-shaped, ribbed leaves&lt;br /&gt;•Small, brownish, cylindrical to pineapple-shaped flower with protruding white stamens on a smooth, slender, leafless stem&lt;br /&gt;•Fibrous roots</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Pull off the leaves or flowers with your fingers, or sever the rosette from the roots with a pocketknife.</harvesting>
    <cooking>This is one of the worst edible plants to use for food. Although you could eat the young leaves when they first appear in early spring, they're rather tough, and taste like wheat grass juice—a flavor few people favor. And the smaller leaves toward the center of the rosette are just as bad later on! Roasting the leaves, like I've done with its relative, common plantain, doesn't work with this species, and the seeds are way too small to use.</cooking>
    <nutrition>Long-leaf plantain probably has the same nutrients as its relative, common plantain: vitamins C and K, plus calcium, potassium, and sulfur, as well as trace minerals.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>Not a good food, this is an excellent plant for skin irritations. Mash some leaves until they produce juice (some people chew them) and repeatedly apply this to a mosquito bite right after you've been bitten. It will cure the bite in about 15 minutes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It lessens the effects of bee stings, it's good for scrapes, cooking burns, cuts, and poison ivy rash, with anti-inflammatory substances and chemicals that stop bleeding. It also contains allantoin, which promotes cell proliferation and healing.&lt;br /&gt;</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions></cautions>
    <similarPlants>The closely related common plantain has oval, ribbed leaves, and a green, pencil-shaped flower. You can use its leaves the same way.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The word "plantain" refers to the foot-like shape of common plantain's leaf, but it's unrelated to the banana-like plantain. I don't know why they share a name.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>If you've ever wondered why scientific names help clarify which plant you're discussing, check out all these common names: Ribwort, Ribgrass, Plantain, Long Plantain,  English Plantain, Snake Plantain, Black Plantain, Ribble Grass, Black Jack, Jackstraw, Lamb's Tongue, Hen Plant, Wendles, Kemp's Cocks, Costa Canina, Lance-leaf Plantain, Narrow leaved Plantain, Soldier's Herb, Snake Plantain, Buckhorn Plantain, Buck Plantain, Buckhorn, Lanceleaf Indianwheat</commonNames>
    <common>1</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>This common plant isn't very good to eat, but it's handy to have around because it's so effective in healing skin irritations such as mosquito bites and scrapes.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser></teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated></similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon></veryCommon>
    <plantImage>
      <id>56</id>
      <title>1)Long-leaf Plantain in Flower</title>
      <slug>1long-leaf-plantain-in-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The basal rosette of narrow, ribbed leaves makes this plant distinct whether or not it has its inconspicuous, long-stemmed, pineapple-shaped flowers. The leaves of the young, nonflowering rosette are edible, but not very tasty, but all the leaves are great, crushed, for mosquito bites and other skin irritations, and the plant grows in sunny, grassy places worldwide.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/LongLeafPlantainPaintingsUnlabeled.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>57</id>
      <title>2)Long-leaf Plantain Young Basal Rosette</title>
      <slug>2long-leaf-plantain-young-basal-rosette</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>If you're going to try eating these tough leaves, do so now, while they're still young, and less tough than they will be later on!</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/LongLeafPlantainRosetteUnlabeled.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>58</id>
      <title>3)Long-leaf Plantain in Flower</title>
      <slug>3long-leaf-plantain-in-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The small, cylindrical flowers atop the slender, leafless flower stalk, and the protruding, white stamens make it easy to recognize this common medicinal plant.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T1290x1823-16954.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>59</id>
      <title>4)Long-leaf Plantain Flower</title>
      <slug>4long-leaf-plantain-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The small, brown base, green, pineapple-shaped top, and protruding, white stamens, all growing on a slender flower stalk, make this small, inconspicuous flower distinct.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T880x2049-15511.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>60</id>
    <title>Asiatic Dayflower</title>
    <slug>asiatic-dayflower</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Commelina communis&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group></group>
    <plantType>
      <id>61</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.40093700 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <annual>1</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>0</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>62</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.41492100 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>63</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.43120500 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>Asiatic dayflower leaves and flowers are in season from mid-spring to mid-fall, although toward the end of the season, many of the leaves start to get ratty-looking, and their food quality goes down. The seeds are in season from summer to mid-fall.</season>
    <habitat>Asiatic dayflower grows in cultivated and disturbed areas, untended gardens, open places in woods, and on rocky soil.</habitat>
    <range>Asiatic dayflower grows throughout the Northeast US. Its similar, larger, edible relative, Virginia dayflower (&lt;i&gt;C. virginica&lt;/i&gt;) grows in the southeast, with the ranges overlapping partially. Other similar edible Southeastern relatives grow westward to Texas or New Mexico.</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Asia</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for a medium-sized plant with two blue petals and one tiny transparent-white one, and grass-like, hairless, stalkless leaves, with bases that wrap around the stem.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This hairless plant with distinct blue flowers usually grows only up to one foot tall, although under very favorable circumstances, it can reach a height of three feet. The first edible wild plant I ever identified, it's very common and an excellent wild food. Very common, it's the first edible wild plant I ever identified, and an excellent wild food.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The simple, smooth-edged, pointed, lance-shaped, grass-like, alternate leaves grow from three to five inches long. Their stalkless bases wrap around the stem to form a sheath.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It bears two upper sky-blue petals about 0.5 inch long, and a smaller, inconspicuous, translucent-white lower petal. Each flower lives for only one day, but the large stands keep producing more flowers for months.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Two short, elliptical sepals fuse to partially enclose two small, pale, yellow-green, slightly elongated pea-like seeds.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Medium-sized, virtually hairless plant under one foot tall&lt;br /&gt;•Two upper blue petals 1/2 inch across&lt;br /&gt;•Smaller translucent-whitish petal below&lt;br /&gt;•Stalkless, alternate, grass-like leaves three to five inches long&lt;br /&gt;•Leaf bases wrapping around the stem&lt;br /&gt;•Small seeds resembling green peas inside a sheath</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Strip off the leaves, flowers, tender portions of the stems, and seeds with your fingers. Avoid any old, coarse, browning plants.</harvesting>
    <cooking>The leaves, flowers, young stems (while they're still tender), and seeds are fine in salads and they're superb in soups or other vegetable dishes. They taste like string beans, and cook in about 10 minutes. Kids have fun picking out the seeds, which taste like green peas, and eating them separately, even though this is time-consuming.</cooking>
    <nutrition></nutrition>
    <medicinalUses></medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions></cautions>
    <similarPlants>Virginia dayflower (&lt;i&gt;C. virginica&lt;/i&gt;), also edible, is similar but larger. It grows in the Southeast. Other similar-looking close relatives in the South and Southwest are also edible.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Spiderwort (&lt;i&gt;Tradescantia virginiana&lt;/i&gt;) looks similar, but with three blue petals, not two, and it grows much larger. It's leaves are edible when they're very young, before they get tough.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Some non-poisonous grasses have similar leaves but totally different flowers, but they're way too hairy to tempt anyone to try to bite into them! </similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames></commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Linneaus named the genus &lt;i&gt;Commelina&lt;/i&gt; after the Commelin family, which produced three sons. Two, represented by the two blue petals, were famous Dutch botanists, but the thrid son, represented by the pale, inconspicuous flower, was a n'er-do-well. His business ventures failed, he went into debt, the woman he loved married someone else, and he died young (outside of that, he had a great life!)</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant></medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Spiderwort</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <plantImage>
      <id>64</id>
      <title>4)Immature Asiatic Dayflower Stand</title>
      <slug>4immature-asiatic-dayflower-stand</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>These plants, with smooth-edged, alternate, pointed, grass-like, stalkless leaves, grow in dense stands in gardens, parks, roadsides, and disturbed habitats.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/AsiaticDayflower.Young.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>65</id>
      <title>1)Asiatic Dayflower Flower and Seeds</title>
      <slug>1asiatic-dayflower-flower-and-seeds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The two bright blue petals hide the inconspicuous transparent white one underneath. The pointed, smooth-edged, alternate, grass-like leaves' bases wrap around the stem. The small, pea-like seeds grow in pairs.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Asiatic Dayflower Flower.Seeds.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>66</id>
      <title>2)Asiatic Dayflower's Flower</title>
      <slug>2asiatic-dayflowers-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The two larger sky-blue petals overshadow the pale white one underneath, leading Linneaus to name the genus &lt;i&gt;Commelina&lt;/i&gt;, after a family with three brothers. Two were famous botanists. The third was a ne'er-do-well: His business failed, he went into debt, the woman he loved married someone else, and he died young (outside of that, he had a great life)!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The three brown stamens at the bottom produce pollen, but the three brown-centered yellow ones on top lost that function. Although sterile, they still help attract insects. </caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T756x1092-15564.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>67</id>
      <title>3)Asiatic Dayflower Seeds</title>
      <slug>3asiatic-dayflower-seeds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The paired, ellipsoid, yellow-green seeds rest in the elliptical fused sepals.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Asiatic Dayflower Seeds.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>69</id>
    <title>Common Mallow</title>
    <slug>common-mallow</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Malva neglecta&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family: &lt;i&gt;Malveae&lt;/i&gt;, the mallow family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>70</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.60776600 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <annual></annual>
      <biennial></biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine></vine>
      <shrub></shrub>
      <tree></tree>
      <seaweed></seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>71</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.61806500 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>72</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.63428300 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>Common Mallow is in season from early spring to late fall—all year where winters are very mild.</season>
    <habitat>Common mallow grows in sunny and partially shaded cultivated habitats such as gardens and parks, and along roadsides, in empty lots, and on disturbed soil.</habitat>
    <range>Most of North America</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for dense stands of creeping or upright plants with small,  pleated, roundish, notched, long-stalked leaves and small, pinkish, notched, hibiscus-like flowers. It's small, disk-shaped fruits look like wheels of cheese.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This plant, which arises from a long, slender taproot, can creep along the ground or grow upright.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The crinkled, rounded to heart-shaped, toothed, slightly hairy, long-stalked basal leaves, and the similar alternate leaves on the main stem, grow from 0.75 to 2.5 inches across, with five to seven shallow lobes. The leaf stalks can grow as long as seven inches and the leaf is notched where it connects to the leaf stalk.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;White to pale-pink or lavender, the five-petaled, long-stalked flowers arise from the leaf axils.  Each flower, under 0.75 inches across, has five petals, with a bushy column of many stamens and one pistil in the center. Pink lines run the length of the petals, which are notched at the tips.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;0.25 inch across, the flattened, rounded, stalked, segmented fruit is called a cheese because it resembles a tiny wheel of cheese.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Long-stalked, pleated, notched leaves .75 to two inches across&lt;br /&gt;•Small, notched, lined, pinkish hibiscus-like flowers with bushy stamens&lt;br /&gt;•Small, flattened, disk-shaped fruits .25 inch across resembling wheels of cheese&lt;br /&gt;•Slender taproot</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Hold down the stems with one hand and strip of leaves, flowers, and fruit with the other. Kids like to pick and eat the fruits one at a time.</harvesting>
    <cooking>The chewy leaves, flowers, and fruits, which cook in about 10 minutes, impart a pleasant, mild flavor to salads, stews, grain dishes, and casseroles—especially good complimenting more flavorful ingredients. Like okra, this mucilaginous vegetable will thicken soups slightly. They're also fine raw, in salads.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Kids love devouring the cheeses right off the plants as quickly as they can find them, and I enjoy the cheeses so much, I eat them at every opportunity, even though I'm a vegan!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;People have tried boiling the roots to obtain a thickener, and cooked to eat, as with the much larger relative, the marsh mallow, but they're way to small and fibrous to be worthwhile.</cooking>
    <nutrition>Common mallow's a good source of vitamin C, iron, calcium, copper, and trace minerals.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>Like its larger relative, the marsh mallow, tea made by boiling the roots is externally and internally soothing. It's supposed to be good for skin sores, stomach and duodenal ulcers, digestive tract irritations, and urinary tract irritations or cystitis, as well as sore throats, irritated air passages, coughs, and bronchitis, and has been used as such for centuries but never been subject to vigorous testing, so its effectiveness is still not confirmed.&lt;br /&gt;</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions></cautions>
    <similarPlants>Related species, such as the marsh mallow, which grows in swamps, are also edible, but so much larger, it would be hard to confuse with this small species.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ground ivy leaves, also edible, resemble common mallow's, but they smell minty, the leaves' upper surfaces are hairy, and the stems are square.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Buttonweed, Cheeseplant, Cheeseweed, Dwarf Mallow, Roundleaf Mallow</commonNames>
    <common>1</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive></invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Common mallow is a mellow, mild-flavored, addition to soups and stews that include stronger-flavored ingredients. It's an excellent addition to salads as well.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated></similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon></veryCommon>
    <plantImage>
      <id>73</id>
      <title>1)Mature Common Mallow</title>
      <slug>1mature-common-mallow</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>Common mallow's long-stalked, roundish, pleated leaves, small five-petaled flowers and fruits resembling wheels of cheese, make it easy to recognize.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/CommonMallowDrawingUnlabeled6.tiff</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>74</id>
      <title>2)Common Mallow in Fruit</title>
      <slug>2common-mallow-in-fruit</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The long-stalked, crinkled, rounded, toothed, slightly hairy, lobed, alternate leaves' axils also give rise to the hibiscus-like, lavender, five-petaled flowers, as well as the flattened, rounded, stalked, segmented fruits that resemble a tiny wheels of cheese.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/CommonMallowInFlower.Fruit.3.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>0</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>75</id>
      <title>3)Common Mallow Flowers</title>
      <slug>3common-mallow-flowers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The small, five-petaled flowers' bushy mixture of stamens and pistil in the center, plus the pink-lined petals, make them quite distinct.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1220x1544-21060.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>76</id>
    <title>Curly Dock</title>
    <slug>curly-dock</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Rumex crispus&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family: &lt;i&gt;Polygonaceae&lt;/i&gt;, the knotweed or smartweed family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>77</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.76369700 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>78</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.77898000 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>79</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.79614800 1291972537</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>The basal leaves are in season in early spring, although there's sometimes new grow in late fall. The immature flower stalk and its leaves are in season in mid-spring, before the plant becomes too bitter to eat.</season>
    <habitat>Sunny and partially shaded, disturbed habitats, fields, and along roadsides and riverbanks.</habitat>
    <range>Throughout the US and southern Canada.</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for a large, coarse plant with long, broad basal leaves with very curly margins. The long clusters of tiny, green flowers or long clusters of tiny, reddish seeds, grow on narrow, branching flower stalks with narrow, wavy, alternate leaves.&lt;br /&gt;</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This large, common spring green forms delicious basal rosettes early on, followed by tasty immature flower stalks.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A basal rosette with hairless, toothless, stalked leaves, growing up to two feet long and up to nearly 2.5 inches wide, appears in early spring. The leaves' very wavy margins make them distinct.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In mid-spring, a branched stem growing up to three feet tall appears, with narrow, alternate, very wavy edged leaves with shorter leaf stalks than the basal leaves'. The base of the leaf stalk forms a sheath that wraps around the stem.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Many small, inconspicuous, green flowers, followed by numerous hard, reddish-brown seeds grow in dense clusters on the stem's branches, in summer and fall.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A large, hard, distinctively yellow, branching taproot often gives rise to several stems.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Basal rosette with large, long, narrow, hairless, toothless, very wavy edged leaves&lt;br /&gt;•Smaller, long, narrow, hairless, toothless, very wavy edged alternate leaves on a tall, branching stem in late spring and summer&lt;br /&gt;•Branching, upright spikes up to three feet tall covered with many, tiny, inconspicuous green flowers, in summer&lt;br /&gt;•Hundreds of tiny, reddish-brown seeds in upright spikes three feet tall, in autumn&lt;br /&gt;•Large, hard, yellow, branching taproot</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Tear off the basal leaves with your hands or cut them off with a knife, scissors, or a shears. Cut off the immature flower stalks with a knife or shears. Dig up the root with a shovel (or use a trowel if you prefer to struggle.) </harvesting>
    <cooking>In early spring, before the flower stalk appears, the basal leaves are excellent raw, in salads and sandwiches, and even better cooked. They cook surprisingly quickly, in about 2 minutes. The young leaf stalks are a little too tough to eat raw, but they cook in 2 to 3 minutes as well. The peeled immature flower stalks, which you collect in mid-spring, are good raw and excellent cooked as well.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Curly dock as a wonderful lemony flavor raw, and the flavor intensifies when you cook it. Steam the leaves and stalks until just wilted (see the accompanying recipe), bake them in casseroles, or add them to soups or stews a couple of minutes before the cooking time ends.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Other writers have made a big deal about the dangers of curly dock's oxalic acid content, but this is completely wrong. There's no evidence of harm to any healthy individual eating large quantities of curly dock or spinach, which contains the same substance (although anyone with kidney disease warned about spinach by their doctor should use the same caution with curly dock), whereas thousands of people have been eating these plants for thousands of years and benefited from them. Just look at Popeye, who's been around since the 1920s!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Although the seed clusters look like a very tempting source of food, the very tiny seeds inside are encased in so many layers of inedible tissues that anyone trying to harvest and use them winds up eating 99% chaff. Nevertheless, if you spend enough harvesting and preparing this trash, your brain may convince you that you're eating real food to justify all the hard work! </cooking>
    <nutrition>Curly dock is a great source of vitamin A and iron (herbalists prescribed it for anemia back in the day, and if the anemia was caused by iron deficiency, it worked), and a good source of vitamins B1, B2, B3, and C, as well as the minerals potassium, calcium, manganese, and phosphorus.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>Curly dock has been used as a blood purifier or detoxifier, especially useful for skin conditions, glandular inflammations, and swellings, for centuries. It contains rumicin, a liver decongestant that stimulates the liver to produce bile, which research has shown helps the body expel heavy metals. A decoction has been used as a bitter tonic for the stomach, where another active ingredient, emodin, stimulates peristalsis, helping with constipation, although large overdoses may cause  nausea or diarrhea. It has even been shown to slow the growth of cancer.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The root's tannin content makes it astringent, and it's been used externally to stop the bleeding, most famously when Dr. Crusher spotted it growing on another planet, and had Capt. Picard apply the yellow taproot to stop her wound from bleeding, in an episode of "Star Trek—The Next Generation."&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It also contains anthraquinones, good for ringworm and other fungal skin infections. In England, they rub the crushed leaves on cure nettle stings, while reciting: “Nettles in, dock out,” and the herb if not the rhyme, works.&lt;br /&gt;</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes>0</hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>The very youngest curly dock leaves, when they've just emerged from the ground and are no more than 2 or 3 inches long, can sometimes temporarily make your tongue numb if you eat them raw, perhaps from a concentration of oxalic acid crystals. Light cooking eliminates this problem.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And never confuse curly dock with Moe dock or Larry dock (Nyuk! Nyuk! Nyuk!)</cautions>
    <similarPlants>"Dock" means deduct or remove, and unrelated plants that people remove from their gardens, such as burdock &lt;i&gt;(Arctium spp.&lt;/i&gt;), have the same confusing last name. Burdock, with a whitish, not yellow, edible root, and an edible immature flower stalk, has broad leaves without wavy margins that are finely whitish and wooly underneath.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On the other hand, the related bitter dock or broadleaf dock (&lt;i&gt;Rumex obtusifolia&lt;/i&gt;) has large leaves that do resemble curly dock's, and the plants sometimes grow side-by-side, but bitter dock has broader leaves without wavy margins. Although nonpoisonous, all parts of this plant usually taste so bad, they remind me of school lunch!</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Curled Dock, Yellow Dock, Sour Dock, Narrow Dock, Narrow-leaved Dock, Garden Patience</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>This common "weed" has delicious leaves, in season in the spring and fall, and the yellow taproot's a major traditional herbal medicine.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Bitter Dock, Burdock</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <plantImage>
      <id>80</id>
      <title>2)Curly Dock Leaf and Seed Spikes</title>
      <slug>2curly-dock-leaf-and-seed-spikes</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The narrow basal leaf of the young plant, with its wavy margins, and the branching spikes of tiny seeds of the mature plant, are what you want to look for to identify this plant in both of its different forms.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/CurlyDockLeafSeedsDrawing.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>81</id>
      <title>3)Curly Dock Basal Rosette and Taproot</title>
      <slug>3curly-dock-basal-rosette-and-taproot</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The stout taproot, yellow under the dirt, or where cut or scraped, and the large, narrow, hairless, toothless leaves, with very wavy margins, make the identity of this young plant beyond doubt.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1792x1572-21139.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>82</id>
      <title>1)Curly Dock Immature and Mature</title>
      <slug>1curly-dock-immature-and-mature</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>The immature plant (right), with its basal rosette of long, narrow, wavy-margined, smooth-edged leaves, as well as the mature plant (left), with similar, smaller, alternate leaves, and dense clusters of flowers and tiny seeds on upright spikes, both have the same yellow taproot.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/CurlyDockPaintingsUnlabeled.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>83</id>
      <title>4)Curly Dock Flowers</title>
      <slug>4curly-dock-flowers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>These tiny green flowers depend on wind for pollination. This is inefficient [so] there have to be many of them, but because no insects are involved in pollination, they can afford to be small and inconspicuous. Note how the flower clusters and leaf stalks form characteristic sheathes around the stem.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T500x493-15357.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>84</id>
      <title>5)Curly Dock Seeds</title>
      <slug>5curly-dock-seeds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:37</dateadded>
      <caption>These tiny, reddish-brown seeds, growing in the hundreds on branching spikes, hide inside so much inedible material that there's no way to turn them into a meal. People grind up the entire mass and use it as flour, and wind up eating mostly chaff—harmless, but not particularly tasty. With this plant, it's best to stick to the tasty young leaves and stems.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/CurlyDockSeedsFragment.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <recipe>
      <id>87</id>
      <title>Stalking the Wild Curly Dock</title>
      <slug>stalking-the-wild-curly-dock</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <directions>Here’s a wonderful lemony-flavored dish you can serve as a side dish or as an appetizer, based on seasoned, baked curly dock flower stalks and leaf stalks.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2-2/3 cups young curly dock flower stalks or leaf midribs, chopped&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. Vegan Garlic Butter&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. salt	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Combine all ingredients in an oiled baking dish and bake, covered, in a preheated 350 degree oven for 25 minutes.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 4 to 6&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Baking time: 30 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn>http://dev.winterroot.net/deepwinter/foraging/cms#pageId-26</dependsOn>
    </recipe>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>88</id>
    <title>Common Dandelion</title>
    <slug>common-dandelion</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Taraxacum officinale&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family &lt;i&gt;Asteraceae  (Compositae)&lt;/i&gt;, the astor or composite family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>89</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.10474300 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>90</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.12041000 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>91</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.13756600 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>The youngest leaves are good to eat in early spring, when they first appear, and in late fall, when new leaves emerge. The crowns and flower buds appear in early spring too, soon after the young leaves. The plants all flowers later in early spring, when the flowers are at their best, although some continue to bloom in the summer and fall. The taproot is in season spring, summer, and fall—also in winter where winters are very mild and there are enough leaves left to locate it.</season>
    <habitat>Lawns, roadsides, meadows, cultivated areas, disturbed habitats</habitat>
    <range>Throughout North America and worldwide</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for a basal rosette of hairless leaves with downward-pointing (toward the leaf base), large, jagged teeth, a slender, hairless, leafless, unbranched flower stalk, a yellow composite flower with ray flowers but no disk flowers, and a fluffy, white, spherical seed head with tiny brown seeds.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>One of the best-known wild edibles and most hated lawn weeds, everyone recognizes the flowers, but getting the youngest, tasty leaves when they're tasty, before the flowers appear takes a bit of attention.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The jagged leaves grow from three to 12 inches long and 0.5 to 2.5 inches wide, always growing in a basal rosette. The leaves' large teeth always point toward the leaf base, not outward or toward the leaf tip.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A cluster of short, stubby, green, flattened, rounded flower buds form in the middle of the basal rosette before the individual, smooth, green, slender flower stalks lift each bud individually two to 18 inches above the ground. The yellow composite flowers, one to two inches wide, consist of ray flowers only. Reflexed green bracts bend under each flower. The flower heads change into the familiar, white, spherical seed heads overnight. A tiny, white parachute connects to each tiny, brown seed, which is shaped like a sunflower seed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The thick, brittle, beige, branching, perennial taproot grows up to 10 inches long. All parts of this hairless plant exude a white milky sap when broken.&lt;br /&gt;</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Basal rosette of leaves with large teeth pointing toward the leaf base&lt;br /&gt;•Cluster of flattened, rounded, green flower buds at ground level at first&lt;br /&gt;•Familiar yellow composite flowers, each on one hollow, hairless flower stalk&lt;br /&gt;•Spherical cluster of white parachutes attached to tiny, brown seeds&lt;br /&gt;•A white, milky latex anywhere the plant is cut&lt;br /&gt;•No hairs on any part of the plant, and no leaves other than basal leaves</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Collect only the smaller, youngest leaves, when they first come up in early spring and late fall. They become increasingly bitter soon after they appear, especially by the time they flower, and through the rest of the growing season. The bitter leaves aren't harmful, they're just way inferior to the youngest ones. Look around before harvesting, and choose plants with the broadest leaves, which are the best, not the ones where most of the leaves consist mostly of teeth.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While you can certainly grab handfuls of leaves, cutting the root just under the center of the rosette with a pocketknife gets you the entire rosette in an instant, and while it's still intact, you can shake off most of the soil and debris before bagging the plant.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A serrated grapefruit spoon is even better than a pocket knife for cutting and scooping out the very young cluster of flower buds while they're at ground level, in the center of the rosettes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Collect the flowers by hand, and be sure to choose the most brightly colored ones. These are the freshest, tastiest ones, especially abundant during the peak of the flowering period, toward the end of early spring. Use a knife to remove the bitter, green sepals, in the field, or at home.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As with most roots, a shovel is the second best implement for digging them up. (The very best implement is a kid—kids love digging, and you won't have to lift a finger before you have a bagful of roots!) Since dandelions are so common, you can be picky about where you're going to dig them up Choose relatively rock-free soil, and dig after periods when rain, when digging is the easiest. </harvesting>
    <cooking>Add the youngest leaves, or their white bases alone, called "crowns," or the flowers (without their bitter sepals) raw to salads. They're quite tasty, strongly flavored with an overtone of bitterness. If the slight bitterness bothers you, use them sparingly, include strong-flavored ingredients, such as wild onions (&lt;i&gt;Allium spp.&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sautéeing dandelion leaves or crowns shrinks them and concentrates this bitterness, but it miraculously vanishes if you cook them further in a sauce, especially if you include spices. I sautée them 10 minutes, then simmer another 10 minutes, using a cooking oil, spices, and sauce that come from the same culinary tradition. You can make a side dish this way, or include pasta, grain, bread cubes, or other sources of protein to make a dandelion-based entrée.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You can sautée the flower buds, or after removing the sepals, the flowers too. They taste somewhat like carrots, so sautéeing the two vegetables together in olive oil, seasoned with mint and marjoram, plus a dash of white wine plus salt and pepper to taste, works especially well, and the carrots' sweetness offsets the flowers' slight bitterness. Or stir the flowers into pancake batter and cook on a griddle like you'd cook pancakes, to make dandelion fritters. The flowers are also famous for making dandelion wine.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Some people cook and eat the taproots. I've found them too bitter and fibrous—way inferior to other wild root vegetables. Conceivably, they youngest taproots might be better, but since the dandelion's a perennial, there's no way to determine in advance which taproots are the youngest.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;People have also roasted the taproots until black, ground them, and used them for making coffee. As someone who doesn't like coffee, I've never tried it myself.</cooking>
    <nutrition>The leaves have more beta-carotene, the precursor of vitamin A, than carrots, and more iron and calcium than spinach. They also provide vitamins B1, B2, B5, B6, B12, C, E, P, and D, plus biotin, inositol, potassium, phosphorus, magnesium, and zinc. The flowers provides beta carotene tool. Oh, and, if I didn't already mention it, eating dandelion leaves is good for you!</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>People have been drinking a decoction of dandelion roots, made by boiling 1 tbs. of the chopped root in 1 cup of water, as a tonic, since prehistoric times. It contains inulin, a polysaccharide that doesn't elicit an insulin response—good for diabetics and hypoglycemics.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Due to the glycoside taraxacin, it's especially good for the liver and gallbladder, where it promotes the flow of bile, reduces inflammation of the bile duct, and helps get rid of gall stones. It’s good for chronic hepatitis, where it reduces liver swelling and jaundice, and it helps indigestion caused by insufficient bile.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The decoction's also a diuretic, and has been used for centuries or kidney problems and water retention.</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Dandelion root decoction should be avoided in cases of irritable stomach or bowel, or if there's acute inflammation, but that's not the greatest danger this plant can pose: Eating the dandelion that grows just inside Central Park's West 81 St. entrance can be extremely dangerous, as exemplified by what happened after I ate 1 of its leaves at 4 PM, March 29, 1986:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Turns out two undercover park rangers had infiltrated my foraging tour. They said they were married, and never held hands or kissed, so I believed them! The man took pictures, I held up the specimens to his camera, only I was the specimen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After I ate the dandelion, they radioed the other rangers with hidden walkie-talkies. I was suddenly surrounded, handcuffed, searched (don't know if they were looking for weeds or "weed"), and hauled off to the Central Park police station, where they took fingerprints and mugshots, then searched my backpack. Fortunately, I had eaten all the evidence!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;They issued me a summons for criminal mischief for removing vegetation from the park because I had eaten the dandelion. I had to go to court, and could face a year in jail. But they then committed a major blunder: They let me go.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I went home and spent the next day on the phone notifying the press. The following morning, on my way to the newsstand, 5 cops came after me, but they all wanted my autograph! I was front page news around the country, and appeared on everything from The CBS Evening News to Late Night with David Letterman.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When I was arraigned in court, I served "Wildman's" Five-Boro Salad to reporters and passersby on the steps of the Manhattan Criminal Courthouse, and the press ate it up! After a second round of media circus, the mayor ordered the parks commissioner who had masterminded the sting operation, Henry Stern, to turn over a new leaf. Stern negotiated with me, dropped the charges, hired me to lead foraging tours throughout the NYC parks system, and wrote a complimentary blurb for my subsequent book. I worked as a Parks Dept. naturalist for the next four years before leaving to resume freelance work after a subsequent administration reneged on the negotiated agreement of the predecessors.</cautions>
    <similarPlants>The common dandelion has no poisonous look-alikes. You can use other similar but less widespread &lt;i&gt;Taraxacum&lt;/i&gt; species the same way you'd use the common dandelion.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Other edible relatives, all with a white, milky latex, look very similar when young, but they're very different when they get older:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Chicory's young leaves' teeth, which are smaller than dandelions' and are sometimes rounded, don't always point to the leaf bases, and there's often a reddish color on the leaf midrib. When it gets older, it grows a stem several feet tall and bears blue flowers. Dead sticks from the previous year's woody stem persist, arising from the basal rosette, into early spring.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Wild lettuce is also edible. Its young basal leaves resemble dandelions', but has more shallow teeth that don't all point toward the leaf base. The leaves have at least some hairs, they're triangular in cross section, and the plant gets much taller than the dandelion. The flowers grow in groups, not individually, and it has fibrous roots, not a taproot.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sow thistle also edible and with taller with yellow flowers, has bristly leaves.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Lions Tooth, Priest Crown, Swine's Snout</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses>
      <id>2577</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.00871200 1300001476</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:16</dateadded>
      <salad></salad>
      <potherb></potherb>
      <root></root>
      <nut></nut>
      <seed></seed>
      <seasoning></seasoning>
      <tea></tea>
      <fruitBerry></fruitBerry>
      <coffee></coffee>
      <flout></flout>
      <pickles></pickles>
      <other></other>
    </foodUses>
    <edibleParts>
      <id>2578</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.08072400 1300001476</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:16</dateadded>
      <leaves></leaves>
      <flower></flower>
      <root></root>
      <nut></nut>
      <seed></seed>
      <stem></stem>
      <fruitBerry></fruitBerry>
      <pod></pod>
      <bud></bud>
      <shoot></shoot>
      <twigs></twigs>
    </edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>French people used to say that dandelions make you pee, referring to the diuretic effect of the decoction of the roots, which are used for kidney problems. But kids, hearing the word &lt;i&gt;dandelion,&lt;/i&gt; thought of the flower.  One kid would tease another by sneaking a dandelion into their pocket, and announce that the victim would wet their bed. Thus they changed the plant's name from &lt;i&gt;dente-de-lion&lt;/i&gt; (lion's tooth) into pisenlit (pee-in-bed)!</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats>
      <id>2580</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.22648500 1300001476</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:16</dateadded>
      <lawns></lawns>
      <fields></fields>
      <thickets></thickets>
      <woodlands></woodlands>
      <marshes></marshes>
      <swamps></swamps>
      <seashore></seashore>
      <disturbed></disturbed>
      <edgeHabitats></edgeHabitats>
      <trailAndRoadside></trailAndRoadside>
      <bogs></bogs>
      <riversLakes></riversLakes>
      <parks></parks>
      <cultiavedPlaces></cultiavedPlaces>
    </primaryHabitats>
    <habitats>
      <id>2579</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.15115600 1300001476</slug>
      <dateadded>2011-03-12 23:31:16</dateadded>
      <lawns></lawns>
      <fields></fields>
      <thickets></thickets>
      <woodlands></woodlands>
      <marshes></marshes>
      <swamps></swamps>
      <seashore></seashore>
      <disturbed></disturbed>
      <edgeHabitats></edgeHabitats>
      <trailAndRoadside></trailAndRoadside>
      <bogs></bogs>
      <riversLakes></riversLakes>
      <parks></parks>
      <cultiavedPlaces></cultiavedPlaces>
    </habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Wild Lettuce, Chicory, Sow Thistle</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <plantImage>
      <id>92</id>
      <title>1)Dandelion Leaf, Taproot, Flower and Seeds</title>
      <slug>1dandelion-leaf,-taproot,-flower-and-seeds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>The familiar spherical, white seed head points its parachutes outward and holds its seeds in the center, along with some sepals held over from the flower. The flower and seed stalk is leafless, hairless, and hollow.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The yellow composite flower, with green sepals below, consists of many individual ray flowers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The long, stiff, light brown taproot usually includes branches.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The leaf's large teeth always point toward the leaf base, which doesn't happen consistently in related plants.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Each tiny white parachute flies off with one tiny, brown seed, which looks like the seed of the related sunflower, only much smaller.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/DandelionPaintings.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>93</id>
      <title>2)Young Dandelion Basal Rosettes</title>
      <slug>2young-dandelion-basal-rosettes</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>[-Dandelions leaves always grow in a basal rosette, never on a stem.] Unlike related plants, they're hairless, and all the large, sharp teeth always point toward the leaf's base. This is when you want to collect dandelion leaves, while they're still young, well before the flowers appear. Comparatively broad-leaved varieties, such as this one, taste the best. And the fact that several rosettes usually grow crowded together, as here, guarantees you even more food.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1671x1329-16559.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage>0</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>94</id>
      <title>4)Dandelion Flower</title>
      <slug>4dandelion-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>What look like petals are actually individual flowers, called ray flowers, bunched together to form a composite flower head, allowing one insect to pollinate many flowers at once, and helping dandelions become as common as they are. The sepals, modified leaves that enclosed the flower when it was a bud, remain at the flower's base, bent backward or reflexed. They're bitter. Remove them before eating the carrot-flavored flower.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/DandelionFlower.2.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>95</id>
      <title>5)Dandelion Seed Head</title>
      <slug>5dandelion-seed-head</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>The spherical, white seed head, with tiny, brown seeds resembling related sunflower seeds in the center, isn't edible, but you can blow away the seeds and make a wish. And your wish will always come true, so long as you wish for more dandelions!</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/DandelionSeedhead.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>96</id>
      <title>3)Dandelion in Flower</title>
      <slug>3dandelion-in-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>[-Dandelions leaves always grow in a basal rosette, never on a stem, even when the plant is flowering. The hairless leaves' large, sharp teeth always point toward the leaf's base.] The yellow, composite flower consists of linear ray flowers, no short disk flowers. And each flower grows on its own smooth, leafless flower stalk. At this stage, you can remove the long, green, bitter sepals at the flower's base and use the flower raw or cooked. The leaves, while not poisonous, are very bitter at this stage.</caption>
      <poisonous>0</poisonous>
      <image>application/media/DandelionInFlower.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>0</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <recipe>
      <id>99</id>
      <title>Dandelions Thai Style</title>
      <slug>dandelions-thai-style</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <directions>Dandelions Thai Style	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Simmering dandelion leaves after sautéing them with spices magically removes their bitterness and makes them especially delicious, even more so with traditional Thai ingredients. Serve over Asian clear (bean thread) noodles.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup coconut oil&lt;br /&gt;9 cups young common dandelion, chicory, or wild lettuce leaves, or other wild or commercial greens&lt;br /&gt;1 cloves of garlic, chopped&lt;br /&gt;1-1/2 cups coconut milk&lt;br /&gt;1-1/2 cups soft tofu, drained and diced&lt;br /&gt;1 tbs. kudzu or arrowroot&lt;br /&gt;1-1/2 tbs. lime juice&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. basil&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. powdered ginger&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. cloves, ground&lt;br /&gt;1-1/2 tsp. salt, or to taste&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. hot sauce, or to taste	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Saute the common dandelion leaves, tofu, and garlic in the oil coconut oil for 10 minutes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Meanwhile, purée the remaining ingredients in a blender.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Add the purée to the dandelions, bring to a boil over medium heat, stirring constantly, reduce the heat to low, cover, and simmer 10 minutes, stirring occasionally.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 4	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation/cooking time: 30 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>100</id>
    <title>Daylily</title>
    <slug>daylily</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Hemerocallis fulva&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family: &lt;i&gt;Hemerocallidaceae&lt;/i&gt;</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>101</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.44440400 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>102</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.45952400 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear>1</allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>103</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.47730400 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>The shoots are in season in early spring, the flowers mainly in late spring and early summer, although a few bloom throughout the summer on cultivated varieties, and the tubers are in season all year.</season>
    <habitat>Cultivated habitats, gardens, roadsides, river banks, parks, open woodlands, and meadows</habitat>
    <range>Most of the US and southern Canada</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Asia</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for long, light green, sword-like basal leaves that become floppy when they get large. Rhizomes spread from the plant's base ending in tubers and large, showy, six-tepaled, orange, funnel-shaped flowers growing atop a slender, leafless stalk.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This colonial perennial produces dense stands of large, showy, edible flowers and flower buds above a basal rosette of long, sword-shaped leaves that you can also eat when they first come up, plus tubers that are in season all year.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The long, narrow, linear, basal leaves, which grow from one to three feet long with parallel veins, flop over as they get longer. When the shoots first appear in early spring, the leaves grow mostly in the same plane, and unite into a short, whitish, cylindrical to elliptoid base that grows one to two inches above ground level. Fleshy, light brown rhizomes under 0.25 inches in diameter spread from the base into the ground, each ending in a small, oblong, light brown tuber, whitish inside, about 0.75 inches long. The true roots emanate from the tubers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Six to 15 large, showy, orange, short-stemmed, upward-facing, funnel-shaped flowers branch from a tall, slender, smooth, unbranched, leafless stem three to four feet tall. Three reflexed tepals, and three nearly-identical sepals, with grow to about four inches long. With ruffled edges, and a pale yellow line runs along each tepal's length. six long, pollen-covered stamens surround a single longer pistil inside each flower.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;During the flowering period, cylindrical, yellow-orange, lined flower buds, growing from 1.5 to three inches long just before they open, grow on the same short branches as the flowers, replenishing the flowers, which wither at the end of the same day that they open. Shriveled remnants of previous days flowers hang from some of the short  branches.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Wild dayliles spread underground and don't set seed.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Sword-shaped leaves of the shoots arising from a cylindrical to ellipsoid, whitish base.&lt;br /&gt;•Rhizomes spreading into the ground from the base, ending in small, potato-like tubers&lt;br /&gt;•A long, unbranched, smooth, leafless flower stalk&lt;br /&gt;•Yellow-orange, cylindrical, lined flower buds&lt;br /&gt;•Large, showy, orange flowers with six tepals&lt;br /&gt;•One pale yellow line running the length of the center of each tepal&lt;br /&gt;•Six stamens and one pistil in each flower&lt;br /&gt;•No fruit or seeds on wild varieties</positiveId>
    <harvesting>One of the easiest renewable edible plants to harvest in quantity, you can twist off and bag handfuls of the shoots under eight inches tall (six inch tall shoots are the best) with your hands, or cut them with a knife or shears. And you can break off the flower buds and flowers with your fingers, and dig up the tubers with a shovel or trowel.</harvesting>
    <cooking>Use the young shoots raw in salads or sandwiches, or steam, sauté, or stir-fry them, and add them to soups, stews, or casseroles. Virtually any cooking method works with them, and their tasty, string bean/onion flavor always, shines through, no matter what other ingredients or spices accompany them. They cook in 10 to 15 minutes. Use shoots under eight inches tall. Larger ones become coarse, unpleasant to eat, and hard to digest.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cook the larger unopened flower buds in recipes that call for green beans. The flavor is similar, and they cook in about 15 minutes. You can also reconstitute the previous day's wilted flowers in soups, or purée; them and use them as a flavorful thickener.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The flowers are sweet and pungent. Don't eat the green bases of the flowers, which are somewhat acrid. Add the flowers to salads that you're going to eat the same day, before they do their Cinderella (or &lt;i&gt;Mission Impossible&lt;/i&gt;) thing the same night. Italian and Chinese cooks dip the flowers in batter and deep-fry them. They're also excellent in soups, sold, dried, as "golden needles" in Chinese grocery stores, for use in traditional hot-and-sour soups. You can stuff the fresh flowers with with dried fruit, nuts, and [-sweetened] vegan cottage cheese mixed with a sweetener and sweet herbs, close them with toothpicks, and serve these stuffed daylilies as a fancy dessert at parties.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You can also scrub and slice the smaller, firm tubers (the larger, older, flaccid ones are terrible), and sauté them in olive oil with garlic, salt, and pepper, or add to soups, stews, or casseroles. They taste a little like nutty turnips. Some people love the tubers, but they are small and labor-intensive to clean, so I rarely prepare them.</cooking>
    <nutrition>No nutritional information about the shoots is available, but the flowers and flower buds provide beta carotene, vitamin C and iron, and the tubers provide protein and essential fatty acids.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>An important herb in Chinese traditional medicine, an infusion made from the flowers is used to treat post-traumatic stress disorders, to cause forgetfulness concerning the traumatic events. Chinese herbalists also use it as a pain-killer, for fever, as a sedative, and for childbirth. These uses need to be verified scientifically.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The rhizomes and tubers have shown antimicrobial and anti-parasitical activity. They may even slow the growth of cancer, although more research is needed to verify this.</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes>1</hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>About 1 out of 50 people can't tolerate daylilies, especially the tubers and shoots, more so if they eat them raw. These people experience diarrhea, sometimes with vomiting. Take a bite or two the first time you try daylilies, and increase your portions by small increments in the following days. If you ever begin to feel queasy or nauseous, avoid this plant. (This caution doesn't apply when my wife's attending a foraging tour—she'd be the 1-out-of-50 people who tolerates this plant about as badly as she tolerates my jokes!)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Also, there are rare genetic variants, otherwise identical to normal daylilies, that will cause such digestive distress in anyone who eats them. I've led hundreds of tours since 1982 where we've collected and eaten daylilies, and have never run into any of these varieties so they must be extremely rare, but there's reliable documentation that this has occurred. Again, try one or two bites the first time you try daylilies in a new location, and avoid collecting from a stand if it makes you a little queasy.</cautions>
    <similarPlants>The tiger-lily’s (&lt;i&gt;Lilium tigruinum&lt;/i&gt;) edible flowers are spotted, not lined, and its stem bears leaves, instead of being bare of leaves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cultivated daylilies come in different colors, sometimes with multiple sets of tepals, and these may even produce seeds. Although edible, they're not as tasty as the wild, orange varieties.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes>Irises (&lt;i&gt;Iris spp.&lt;/i&gt;) and daffodils (&lt;i&gt;Narcissus spp.&lt;/i&gt;) have sword-shaped leaves when young, making them resemble daylily shoots. The flowers, which appear later on, differ greatly, and these plants don't have rhizomes ending in a tubers, so dig up daylilies to make sure you have the right plant before you eat the shoots. </poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Orange Daylily, Tawny Daylily, Tiger Daylily, Ditch Daylily</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered>0</endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Daylilies have edible shoots, flower buds, flowers, and tubers. They're common, widespread, and easy to harvest. Except for people who can't tolerate them, they're a bonanza for foragers. </flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated></similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated>Iris, Daffodil</poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>104</id>
      <title>Daylily Flower Ice Cream</title>
      <slug>daylily-flower-ice-cream</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <directions>Here’s a wonderfully flavored wild ice cream, thanks to these exotic-flavored flowers. You can create an even more unusual dessert, by stuffing additional fresh day-lily flowers with it, and sealing them with toothpicks, just before serving.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3-1/2  cups soy-rice milk, nut milk, or oat milk&lt;br /&gt;1 tbs. arrowroot or kudzu&lt;br /&gt;1 tbs. agar flakes&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup raw pignoli nuts or cashew nuts&lt;br /&gt; 1/2 cup grape seed oil&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup vegetable glycerin&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup lecithin granules&lt;br /&gt;2 tsp. vanilla extract&lt;br /&gt;1 tbs. clear liquid stevia&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. salt&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. orange extract&lt;br /&gt;30 day lily flowers	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Simmer the arrowroot and agar in the soy-rice milk 5 minutes or until the agar is dissolved, stirring often.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Pur&amp;#233e; with the remaining ingredients in a blender.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Freeze in an ice cream machine according to the manufacturer’s directions.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Makes 5-1/2 cups&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 20 minutes&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Freezing time: 2-1/2 hours</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>105</id>
      <title>1)Daylily Shoot, Tubers, Flower Buds, and Flowers</title>
      <slug>1daylily-shoot,-tubers,-flower-buds,-and-flowers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>The shoot's leaves long, narrow spread out mostly along one plane, and light brown rhizomes spread out in all directions from a whitish base, each ending in a tuber with roots. These shoots, about six inches tall, are the best ones to collect effectively and eat.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The stalked, funnel-shaped, six-parted orange flower, with one pistil and six stamens, and a pale yellow line running the length of the tepals, make this distinctive plant easy to spot, and the floppy, linear, basal-only leaves clinches your ID.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The young shoots, tubers, open flowers, unopened orange flower buds, and the wilted flowers on the short branches at the top of the leafless flower stalk are all good to eat.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/DaylilyFlowerPaintings.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>106</id>
      <title>2)Daylily Shoots</title>
      <slug>2daylily-shoots</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>These light green shoots with curved, linear, smooth-edged, pointed leaves can take openings in the forest.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J2272x1704-16378.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>107</id>
      <title>3)Daylily Flowers and Flower Buds</title>
      <slug>3daylily-flowers-and-flower-buds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>These showy, orange, short-stalked, funnel-shaped flowers consist of three similar petals and sepals (a.k.a. six tepals), each with a yellow line running down its length; six stamens covered with pollen at the tip, and one pistil.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[-The flowers taste as good as they look. Delicious cooked in soups, stews, or casseroles, you can also use these cylindrical, orange-yellow flower buds, which grow on short, branched stems at the top of the leafless flower stalk, in recipes that call for string beans. Once you taste one, you'll know that this bud's for you!]</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T2272x1704-15631.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>110</id>
      <title>4)Daylily Tubers</title>
      <slug>4daylily-tubers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>The underground parts distinguish the daylily from poisonous look-alikes before the flowers appear: Slender, light brown rhizomes spread from the white base. Each rhizome ends in a light brown, oblong tuber, from which the true roots grow.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/DaylilyTubers.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>111</id>
    <title>Epazote</title>
    <slug>epazote1</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Dysphania ambrosioides, Teloxys ambrosioides&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>&lt;i&gt;Chenopodiaceae&lt;/i&gt;, the goosefoot family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>112</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.74948400 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <annual>1</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>0</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>113</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.76438800 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>114</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.78148200 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>Mid-spring through fall</season>
    <habitat>Sunny habitats, roadsides, gardens, parks, and disturbed soil</habitat>
    <range>Native to Mexico and Central America, it grows across the US.</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Meso-America</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for a branching, medium-sized plant with long, oval, wavy-toothed leaves, a strong, resinous smell, and tiny yellowish or white five-petaled flowers hidden in masses of green flower buds and fruits.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This fragrant, weedy-looking, branching plant, which grows one to three feet tall, is important as a culinary seasoning and medicinal herb.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The wavy-toothed, two to four inches long leaves are oblong to lance-shaped, tapering at the base and tip. Clusters of tiny, inconspicuous, white or yellowish, five-petaled flowers, hidden in masses of green flower buds, followed by masses of tiny, green fruits arise on spikes from the leaf axils of the top branches of this wind-pollinated plant.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The whole glandular-dotted, slightly hairy plant has a strong, resinous fragrance. It smells like pine if you like it, or stinks like turpentine if you don't.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Branching, slightly hairy plant, one to three feet tall&lt;br /&gt;•Alternate, wavy-edged, oblong to lance-shaped leaves, two to four inches long&lt;br /&gt;•Green masses of inconspicuous, white or yellowish, five-petaled flowers, on spikes arising from the upper leaf axils&lt;br /&gt;•Strong, resinous odor</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Strip off the leaves to use as a seasoning. If the flowers or fruits come off too, that's fine. If the plant is very young, you can use the stems too, as long as they're not tough. And you can use the whole plant, except the roots, for making tea.</harvesting>
    <cooking>A major culinary herb in Mexican and Meso-American cuisine, you can use the fresh leaves, finely chopped, or the dried leaves, crumbled, to flavor bean dishes, soups, stews, molés, or sauces. Use sparingly or the strong flavor, a little like tarragon, cilantro, and bay leaves, will overpower the other ingredients.</cooking>
    <nutrition></nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>Loaded with biologically active compounds, an infusion has been used for centuries in Mexico and Central America to kill parasites, especially hookworm. It was even listed in the US Pharmacopeia until it was replaced by synthetic drugs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It's also a carminative, good for indigestion and gas. I never cook beans without adding some epazote, especially before an indoor speaking engagement. And a Nicaraguan man who attended one of my tours said it's name in his country translates to "fart buster!"&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In Brazil, everyone knows it cures hangovers. It's infuriating to me why something so effective hasn't been investigated in lab experiments—it's enough to drive me to drink!</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Don't use epazote as a potherb. It's good for you in small quantities, but poisonous in large quantities.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Don't use this herb if you're pregnant or lactating, and don't take the essential oil (which you'd have to buy, and is used externally for ringworm), extracted from the seeds, internally. It's considered toxic.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Also, there are certain individuals who should never use epazote. It can make them sick or kill them, even in small amounts. But don't worry, you can tell who these individuals are by determining their occupation: it's only harmful to lawyer or politicians—remember, it kills parasites!</cautions>
    <similarPlants>Lamb's-quarters is an edible plant people have confused with epazote, but it has diamond-shaped leaves that are whitish underneath, and virtually no odor.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Mexican Tea, Wormseed, Jesuit's tea</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive></invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Essential in Mexican cuisine, this culinary herb is great for seasoning soups, sauces, guacamole, and beans, it prevents people from getting gas, and it's used in Brazil to cure hangovers.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Lamb's-quarters</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>115</id>
      <title>2)Black Bean Soup with Epazote</title>
      <slug>2black-bean-soup-with-epazote</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <directions>Black Bean Soup with Epazote&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Epazote, plus other traditional Mexican seasonings, creates a wonderful soup that far surpasses what you’d get in a Mexican restaurant. Miso, used in traditional Japanese cuisine, makes it especially creamy, and also adds the right amount of salt.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup olive oil&lt;br /&gt;2 yellow onions, chopped&lt;br /&gt;4 cloves of garlic, chopped&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup mellow miso&lt;br /&gt;1-1/2 cup cooked black beans&lt;br /&gt;2 cups vegetable stock&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup cilantro&lt;br /&gt;The juice of 1/2 a lime&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. Tabasco sauce&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. cumin, ground&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. oregano, ground&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. black peppercorns, ground into 1 tsp.&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tbs. fresh epazote, finely chopped, or 1/4 tsp. dried epazote, ground	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Sauté the onions in the olive oil 15 minutes, or until lightly browned.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Add the garlic and sauté another 5 minutes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Pur&amp;#233e; the onions and garlic with 1 cup of the beans and the remaining ingredients in a blender, in 2 batches.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;4. Bring to a boil with the remaining beans over medium heat, stirring constantly, reduce the heat to low, cover, and simmer for 5 minutes.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 4&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 40 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>116</id>
      <title>1)Young Epazote</title>
      <slug>1young-epazote</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>The alternate, lance-shaped to oblong, coarsely toothed leaves should be enough to let you spot this plant, and the resinous fragrance will confirm its identity.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/EpazoteImmature.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>117</id>
      <title>2)Epazote in Flower</title>
      <slug>2epazote-in-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <caption>This resinous-smelling, branching plant has lance-shaped to oblong, alternate, wavy-toothed leaves. [-While all field guides call the tiny flowers, which grow on spikes arising from the leaf axils, green, you can see that] They have five white petals, and I've seen them with a yellowish tinge too. [-Masses of tiny, green flower buds and similar-looking green fruits normally makes them hard to see, I but spotted their true color after only 28 years of foraging!]</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/EpazoteInFlower.4.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage>0</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <recipe>
      <id>119</id>
      <title>1)Wild Guacamole</title>
      <slug>1wild-guacamole</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <directions>Wild Guacamole&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Epazote, the classic herb of Mexican cuisine, finds its natural home in this south-of-the-border spread.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2 ripe avocados&lt;br /&gt;The juice of half a lemon&lt;br /&gt;2 cloves of garlic, chopped&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tbs. fresh epazote or 1/4 tsp. dried, crumbled epazote, finely chopped&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. Vege-sal or 1/2 tsp. salt, or to taste&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. hot pepper sauce or Tabasco sauce, or to taste&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. cumin, ground&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. black pepper, ground	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mash the avocado with the other ingredients.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Makes 2 cups&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 10 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>120</id>
    <title>Field Pennycress</title>
    <slug>field-pennycress</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Thlaspi arvense&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family: &lt;i&gt;Brassicaceae&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;Cruciferae&lt;/i&gt;, the mustard or cabbage family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>121</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.97908300 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <annual>1</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>0</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>122</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.99348400 1291972538</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:38</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>123</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.01072800 1291972539</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>Early spring to mid-summer</season>
    <habitat>In full sunlight on awns, in fields and meadows, along roadsides, and in disturbed habitats</habitat>
    <range>Throughout most of North America</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for a hairless plant with alternate, lance-shaped leaves that clasp the stem, clusters of small, four-petaled, white flowers, and flattened, circular, notched seedpods.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This common, tasty mustard has distinctive seed pods that look like notched pennies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A hairless plant, the lance-shaped basal leaves, which arise from a taproot, grow one to six inches long. Sometimes lobed, with rounded tips, they disappear when the stem emerges.  With wavy margins, the lance-shaped, alternate stem leaves grow 0.5 to three inches long. Because they lack leafstalks, two lobes from the leaf's base partially encircle or clasp the ridged stem, which grows from six to 18 inches tall.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;From mid-spring to mid-summer, tiny, short-stalked, four-petaled white flowers crowd onto racemes around the stem's tip. They’re followed by circular, flattened, heart-shaped, deeply notched seedpods reminiscent of pennies. These release tiny, dark brown seeds when they mature and dry out.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Crush the plant and you'll smell onions, ruining dairy products when cows eat it, so even though it's very tasty to foragers, farmers call it “stinkweed.”</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Basal rosette of hairless, lance-shaped leaves arising from a rhizome&lt;br /&gt;•Lance-shaped, alternate leaves&lt;br /&gt;•A pair of pointed lobes at the leaf base clasping the stem&lt;br /&gt;•Terminal racemes of tiny, white, four-petaled flowers&lt;br /&gt;•Flat, circular, notched seedpods containing tiny, black seeds&lt;br /&gt;•Onion-like odor when crushed</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Use a pocket knife to sever the rosette from the taproot, or harvest the basal leaves by hand. Strip leaves, flowers or seed pods, and tender pieces of the stems with your fingers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Collect the nearly mature seedpods and store them in a paper bag (which is porous) until they dry out, open up, and release the seeds. Spread on a try, blow away the chaff, and store the seeds in a tightly closed jar before using.</harvesting>
    <cooking>This is a very tasty, fiery-hot mustard, a little like black pepper and wasabe. Use the basal leaves, the leaves on the leafstalk, flowers, seedpods, and tender portions of the stems raw in salads or sandwiches, or cook them using virtually any method for about 10 minutes or until tender. Use sparingly unless you love spicy food.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You can also make prepared mustard by grinding the seeds or green seedpods in a blender with vinegar to cover. Add salt or mellow miso, and turmeric (for yellow coloring) plus other spices typically used in making prepared mustard, , i.e., tarragon, white pepper, or garlic.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If you're a kid, tell your friend the seeds are very sweet and feed some to him or her. You may lose a friend, but you'll laugh your head off!</cooking>
    <nutrition>A good source of vitamin C, for a plant, the leaves are high in protein. They’re also a good source of B-complex vitamins and sulfur.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>An infusion of the seeds supposedly acts as a tonic. This plant has been used in herbal medicine for fevers, coughs, and various infections, and research backs this up—it has antimicrobial properties, suppressing the growth of staphylococcus and streptococcus. The whole plant is also a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory, like aspirin.&lt;br /&gt;</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Eating very large quantities of this plant make cause nausea or dizziness, or inhibit white blood cells, but the plant is way too spicy for this to happen, and such problems have only been observed in cattle, which probably wouldn't be using this app to identify the plant anyway.&lt;br /&gt;</cautions>
    <similarPlants>Other edible members of the mustard family have similar flowers, but the leaves are usually toothed or lobed, they don't clasp the stem, and none has the deeply notched, circular seed pods. Field peppergrass &lt;i&gt;(Lepidium campestre&lt;/i&gt;), for example, is a very similar edible relative with seedpods that aren't notched. Poor man's pepper, with basal leaves with teeth pointing toward the leaf base is another edible relative, as is shepherd's purse, which has triangular seedpods.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Pennycress, Frenchweed, Fanweed, Stinkweed, Mithridate Mustard</commonNames>
    <common></common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive></invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Use this plant any time you want to create a fiery hot dish.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser></teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>field peppergrass, poor man's pepper, shepherd's purse</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon></veryCommon>
    <plantImage>
      <id>124</id>
      <title>1)Field Pennycress in Flower</title>
      <slug>1field-pennycress-in-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The lance-shaped, alternate leaves clasping the stem, along with the tiny flowers on terminal racemes, characterize it before the seeds appear.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/FieldPennycressDrawingTrimmed.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>125</id>
      <title>2)Field Pennycress Flowers</title>
      <slug>2field-pennycress-flowers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The short-stalked, small, five-petaled flowers clustered above the flat, notched fruits make identification of this plant certain.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T618x1085-19574.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>126</id>
      <title>3)Field Pennycress Seeds</title>
      <slug>3field-pennycress-seeds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>These flat, circular, notched seeds account for the plant's name, and make it stand out from all its relatives.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/FieldPennycressSeeds.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>0</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>127</id>
      <title>4)Field Pennycress Flowering</title>
      <slug>4field-pennycress-flowering</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>Field pennycress stands such as this one often spread across sunny, disturbed sites, making it easy to harvest in quantity. The lance-shaped leaves clasp the stem, distinguishing it from its edible relatives at this stage, even without the notched seeds.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/FieldPennycressStandInFlower.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <recipe>
      <id>130</id>
      <title>Thai Peanut Sauce with Field Pennycress</title>
      <slug>thai-peanut-sauce-with-field-pennycress</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <directions>This basic sauce turns virtually any combination of stir-fried ingredients into an authentic-tasting Thai dish, and the field pennycress provides the fire.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup field pennycress seeds or leaves, or to taste&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup peanut butter&lt;br /&gt;2 cups coconut milk&lt;br /&gt;1 pear&lt;br /&gt;The juice of 1 lime&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. peanut oil&lt;br /&gt;2 cloves of garlic&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. fresh cilantro&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. black pepper&lt;br /&gt;1 small red onion&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. brown rice vinegar&lt;br /&gt;3 tbs. tamari soy sauce&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. dark sesame oil	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Purée; all ingredients in a blender.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Transfer to a saucepan and bring to a boil over medium heat, stirring constantly.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Reduce the heat to low and simmer, uncovered, 5 minutes, stirring often.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Makes 4 cups&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[Cooking time: ]15 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>131</id>
    <title>Foxtail Grass</title>
    <slug>foxtail-grass</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Setaria spp.&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family: &lt;i&gt;Poaceae (Gramineae&lt;/i&gt;), true grasses</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>132</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.28976700 1291972539</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>133</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.30497900 1291972539</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>134</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.32158100 1291972539</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>Late summer and early fall</season>
    <habitat>Sunny habitats, wild and cultivated fields, disturbed habitats, parks</habitat>
    <range>Most of North America</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Eurasia</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for grass with a large, cylindrical flower head that resembles a fox's tail.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>The flat, narrow, toothless, parallel-veined leaves of these annual or perennial grasses  grow up to six inches long. The tiny flowers grow on a narrow, curved, unbranched, cylindrical flower heads in the summer. Small, black seeds replace them on the same bristly seed heads in late summer and autumn.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One species,  yellow foxtail (&lt;i&gt;S. pumila&lt;/i&gt;), has an upright seed head, the other one, green foxtail (&lt;i&gt;S. viridis&lt;/i&gt;) has a curved seed head.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The roots are fibrous.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Grass with unbranched, smooth-edged leaves up to six inches long&lt;br /&gt;•Bristly, cylindrical seed heads, straight or curved, resembling a fox's tail</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Wait until the seeds are ripe and fall off when you gently rub the seed heads. Do so over a paper bag, rubbing many seed heads at once. Avoid unripe seed heads, and don't rub hard, or you'll get very annoying hairs that will get stuck between your teeth. </harvesting>
    <cooking>Foxtail grass has a pleasant, nutty flavor and very crunchy texture. Spread the seeds you've harvested on a tray and blow away any chaff with a fan, over the kitchen sink.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Grind the seeds and use them with whole grain flour, for making breads, pancakes, or porridge. You can also cook the seeds in grain dishes, to add crunchiness and flavor. Unlike cultivated grains, foxtail grass seeds never become completely soft, an asset if you like crunchy foods.</cooking>
    <nutrition>Most grains provide protein, B-complex vitamins, and high-quality oils, but this close relative of millet has never been tested.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>People have crushed the whole plant and applied it to bruises, and in Japan, people eat the cooked, ground seeds for digestive disorders, but these uses have never been tested scientifically.</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions></cautions>
    <similarPlants>Other grasses don't have bristly, cylindrical seed heads that look like a fox's tail.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Wild Millet</commonNames>
    <common>1</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive></invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Other wild grain-like seeds are good to eat, but this relative of millet is the the only true wild grain that's easy to harvest.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser></teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated></similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon></veryCommon>
    <plantImage>
      <id>135</id>
      <title>1)Yellow Foxtail Grass</title>
      <slug>1yellow-foxtail-grass</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The black seeds visible in the straight, cylindrical seed heads look like they'll start falling out with just a little rubbing.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/FoxtailGrassPainting.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>136</id>
      <title>2)Green Foxtail Grass</title>
      <slug>2green-foxtail-grass</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The weight of the ripe seeds of this species of foxtail grass looks like it's making this species bend over, but that's the way it grows.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T2108x1604-16106.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>137</id>
      <title>3)Yellow Foxtail Grass Seed Head</title>
      <slug>3yellow-foxtail-grass-seed-head</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The cylindrical seed head of this species stands erect no matter how ripe the seeds get.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Foxtail Grass.Straight1.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <recipe>
      <id>138</id>
      <title>Heavenly Risotto</title>
      <slug>heavenly-risotto</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <directions>Heavenly Risotto	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Here’s a quick, wonderful grain recipe you can make in short order with a pressure cooker. The foxtail grass seeds add some crunchiness in an otherwise soft dish, and, along with the black walnuts, make it even more special.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;4-1/4 cups water or vegetable stock&lt;br /&gt;2 cups long-grain brown rice&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup foxtail grass seeds&lt;br /&gt;1 red onion, chopped&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup mellow miso&lt;br /&gt;2 celery stalks, sliced&lt;br /&gt;4 cloves of garlic, chopped&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. olive oil&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. All-purpose Seasoning (available in health food stores)&lt;br /&gt;1 14-oz. package of dairy-free soy mozzarella cheese, grated&lt;br /&gt;1/2 cup roasted black walnuts or commercial walnuts, chopped	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Bring all ingredients except the nuts to pressure in a pressure cooker and pressure cook under high pressure for 20 minutes, then allow to reach room temperature naturally (or simmer, covered, in a saucepan, 60 minutes, or until all the liquid is absorbed.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Serve topped with the nuts.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 6 to 8&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 15&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cooking time: 25 or 50 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>139</id>
    <title>Garlic Mustard</title>
    <slug>garlic-mustard</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Alliaria petiolata&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family: &lt;i&gt;Brassicaceae&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;Cruciferae&lt;/i&gt;, the mustard or cabbage family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>140</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.49833300 1291972539</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>1</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>0</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>141</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.51358400 1291972539</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>1</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>142</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.52983600 1291972539</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>You can collect the basal leaves and taproots from late fall through early spring, the sprouts in early spring, the leafstalk's leaves in mid-spring, and the seeds from mid-summer to mid-fall.</season>
    <habitat>Woodlands, disturbed habitats, parks, road- and trailsides, edge habitats, and wetlands</habitat>
    <range>Most of North America</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for endless basal rosettes of dark green, heavily veined, long-stalked, coarsely-toothed, heart-shaped leaves. Watch for flower stalks with alternate, triangular to arrow-shaped leaves and racemes of small, white, four-petaled flowers. Also examine woodland floors for the many erect, slender, unbranched, whitish skeletons with narrow, cylindrical, short-stalked, upward-curving, alternate seedpods.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sniff for the fragrance of garlic when you crush the leaves or stem.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This common, healthful, highly invasive woodland biennial has a distinctive garlic smell when crushed, which helps protect it from insects (unless Italian insects find it!)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The sprouts of new plants arising from seeds look like alfalfa sprouts, each with a single, slender, reddish stalk around two inches tall, and a single, strap-shaped leaf around 0.5 inch long. These arise among the basal rosettes coming from taproots of second-year plants, which take over great swaths of forest. Their long-stalked, scallop-edged, deeply-veined, kidney-shaped, garlic-scented leaves grow up to 2.5 inches across. The thin, white taproot smells and tastes like horseradish.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;By mid-spring, second-year plants grow a single erect stem one to 3.5 feet tall, slightly hairy, with more pointed, alternate, deeply veined, larger-toothed, triangular leaves. A broccoli-like flower bud soon gives way to clusters of four-petaled white flowers, each 0.33 inch across. Configured like a cross (typical of the mustard family), they also alternate around the flower stalk. These are soon replaced by long, green, slender, four-parted, cylindrical seedpods, one to 1.5 inches long, curving upward on short stalks.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When the second-year plant dies in the summer, the dry, whitish, short-stalked seedpods split lengthwise to reveal two rows of tiny, oblong, blackish, finely lined, spicy flavored seeds.&lt;br /&gt;</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Basal rosette of long-stalked, coarsely toothed, deeply veined, dark green, heart-shaped leaves&lt;br /&gt;•one to 3.5 feet tall stem with triangular, coarsely toothed leaves&lt;br /&gt;•Small, broccoli-like flower buds&lt;br /&gt;•Clusters of small, white, four-petaled flowers&lt;br /&gt;•Persistent slender, unbranched, upright, white skeleton with many long, narrow, cylindrical, alternate, short-stalked, upward-curved seedpods&lt;br /&gt;•Seedpod skeletons containing rows of tiny, oblong, blackish, ribbed seeds&lt;br /&gt;•Slender, white taproot that smells like horseradish&lt;br /&gt;•Leaves, stem, flower buds, and flowers smelling like garlic when crushed&lt;br /&gt;</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Pick the sprouts with your fingers. It's as easy to pull off handfuls of basal leaves with your fingers too. You can quickly strip leaves, soft parts of the upper stems, flower buds, and flowers from the mature plants.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If the soil is soft and moist, you can sometimes pull on the top of the taproot under the basal rosette with your hand to uproot it. Otherwise, use a shovel or trowel.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gently break off lots of dried seed heads and transfer them into a supermarket paper shopping bag. By the time you get home, many of the seeds will have fallen out of the pods. Rub the pods with your hands to loosen the rest of the seeds over a tray, and use a fan to blow the seeds into your sink. Store the seeds in a tightly closed glass jar, they last indefinitely.</harvesting>
    <cooking>The leaves all taste like garlic, with bitter and spicy overtones. The young leaves on the developing flower stalk and the accompanying flower buds and flowers, which taste hot and sweet as well, are better than the basal leaves in early spring, which are good too. Use them sparingly in any savory recipe, with other flavorful ingredients, to counteract the bitterness that concentrates as cooking shrinks the leaves. You can use any cooking method. They cook ready in about 5 minutes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The basal leaves are edible in the cold weather seasons, but they also have an overtone of bitterness that doesn't disappear when you sauté them and cook them in a liquid, which works with dandelions and its relatives. Use them sparingly in salads or sandwiches. On the other hand, this plant makes superb pestos, where even the bitterness of the cold weather season basal leaves disappears.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Use the seeds to spice up anything you want. Unlike hard commercial mustard seeds, which you usually have to grind, these seeds are soft enough to chew, and they add texture as well as spiciness to any recipe. Since they burn when you sauté them, add [-them] to recipes at the end of the cooking process if possible, to avoid dissipating their flavor. Tthey also work well baked, in place of caraway or poppy seeds in breads and rolls.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Use the horseradish-flavored root just like horseradish for extra spiciness in any recipe. Like horseradish, the flavor is volatile—cooking destroys it. So add this at the end of a recipe, or use raw as a garnish. To preserve the root, grate or finely chop it, cover with vinegar immediately, and refrigerate. This lasts indefinitely.</cooking>
    <nutrition>Garlic mustard is a good source of vitamins A, C, and E, some of the B vitamins, plus potassium, calcium, magnesium, copper, iron and manganese. Like other mustards, it contains plant estrogens that are inert in humans (they're probably designed by natural selection to interfere with insects' development), but block human and synthetic estrogens from promoting the unwanted cell proliferation that can lead to cancer. The sulfur-containing amino acids that give it its garlic odor, like garlic, promote cardiovascular health. Pretty impressive for a despised invasive weed!</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>Not a major traditional medicinal plant, garlic mustard has been little used in herbal medicine, although an infusion of the leaves has been used as a diaphoretic to cause sweating, stimulate the immune system and treat bronchitis. People have heated the root in oil and applied this ointment to the chest for bronchitis too. I have no idea whether or not this works, but juice from the leaves does inhibit the growth of gram negative bacteria, which includes those that cause gastric enteritis and typhoid.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;People have also applied the crushed leaves to insect bites and stings, although I've had such good results with jewelweed and common plantain that I've never tried garlic mustard for bug bites.</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Be careful not to let the seeds drop to the ground when you collect them, especially if you're Catholic. You're not supposed to spill your seeds!</cautions>
    <similarPlants>Common blue violet leaves and other violet species (&lt;i&gt;Viola spp.&lt;/i&gt;), which are edible, look like young garlic mustard's basal leaves, but with their smaller teeth, pointed leaf tips, and no garlic odor, it's easy to tell them apart.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Henbit deadnettle, non-poisonous but musty-smelling, begins with a rosette of heart-shaped leaves like garlic mustard, but they're very hairy, and the stem of this mint is square. And no other plants with heart-shaped leaves smell like garlic when crushed.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Jack-by-the-hedge, Garlic Root, Hedge Garlic, Sauce-alone, Jack-in-the-bush, Penny Hedge, and Poor Man's Mustard</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>This garlic-scented and -flavored plant, which makes the world's best pestos, is unusual because it's better when in flower than when young.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Common Blue Violet, Henbit Deadnettle</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>143</id>
      <title>Simple Garlic Mustard Pesto</title>
      <slug>simple-garlic-mustard-pesto</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <directions>Simple Garlic Mustard Pesto	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Garlic mustard makes of such excellent pesto, that it works superbly with the most simple pesto ingredients. Unusual in pesto, brewer's yeast, also fermented, handily replaces the traditional Parmesan cheese, which, as a vegan, I don't use.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Use this pesto with pasta, as a savory spread on bread or crackers, or mixed into steamed vegetables.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2 cups garlic mustard leaves, flowers and top stems&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup commercial garlic cloves&lt;br /&gt;1-1/2 cups olive oil&lt;br /&gt;1 cup goutweed or parsley&lt;br /&gt;1 cup fresh basil&lt;br /&gt;2 cups black walnuts, commercial walnuts, or pignoli nuts&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup brewer’s yeast&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. salt	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Chop the garlic and goutweed or parsley in a food processor.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Add the remaining ingredients and process into a slightly chunky paste.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Makes 3 cups&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 5 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>144</id>
      <title>2)Garlic Mustard Sprouts</title>
      <slug>2garlic-mustard-sprouts</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The small, strap-shaped, smooth-edged leaf of each reddish sprout hangs from the top like a horizontal flag.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T519x598-16332.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>145</id>
      <title>3)Garlic Mustard Basal Rosette</title>
      <slug>3garlic-mustard-basal-rosette</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The heavily veined, coarse-toothed, long-stalked, kidney-shaped basal leaves all emerge from a hidden central taproot.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1716x1444-18421.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>146</id>
      <title>1)Garlic Mustard Basal Rosette and Taproot</title>
      <slug>1garlic-mustard-basal-rosette-and-taproot</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The slender, long, white, taproot is the source of the long-stalked, deeply veined, coarse-toothed, dark green, kidney-shaped basal leaves, which vary in size.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/GarlicMustardPaintingUnlabled.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>147</id>
      <title>4)Garlic Mustard Flower Stalk</title>
      <slug>4garlic-mustard-flower-stalk</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The alternate leaves on the flower stalk resemble the basal leaves, but the leaf stalks are shorter, and the upper leaves are more triangular than kidney-shaped.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1211x2218-18419.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>148</id>
      <title>5)Garlic Mustard Flower Bud</title>
      <slug>5garlic-mustard-flower-bud</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>The cluster of flower buds, growing above the heavily veined, alternate, triangular, coarsely toothed leaves, looks like a smaller version of its relative, broccoli.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J2044x1508-18415.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>149</id>
      <title>6)Garlic Mustard Flowers</title>
      <slug>6garlic-mustard-flowers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>Garlic mustard's small, white flowers, growing clustered, all have four petals configured like a cross, typical of the mustard family. They grow above the alternate, deeply veined, coarsely toothed, triangular leaves, and among the unopened buds, which still resemble broccoli.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/J1332x1100-18417.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>150</id>
      <title>7)Garlic Mustard Seed Pods</title>
      <slug>7garlic-mustard-seed-pods</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>After garlic mustard dies in its second year, the whitish skeleton bears long, narrow, alternate seed pods curved upward, containing rows of tiny, elongated, blackish seeds.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/GarlicMustardSkeletonWithSeeds.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>151</id>
      <title>8)Garlic Mustard Seeds</title>
      <slug>8garlic-mustard-seeds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <caption>These long, narrow, ribbed, blackish seeds are very easy to collect, and great to use.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/GarlicMustardSeeds.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>153</id>
    <title>Japanese Knotweed</title>
    <slug>japanese-knotweed</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Polygonum cuspidatum, Fallopia japonica&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family: &lt;i&gt;Polygonaceae&lt;/i&gt;, the knotweed or smartweed family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>154</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.99435700 1291972539</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:39</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>155</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.01093200 1291972540</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>156</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.02800500 1291972540</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>You can eat this plant only in early spring, while the shoots are tender. On very rare occasions, new edible shoots come up in the fall after the mature plants have been cut down.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The inedible flowers bloom in the summer, the inedible seeds ripen in the fall, and the inedible dead stalks persist through the winter into the following spring.</season>
    <habitat>Partial shade or full sunlight, disturbed habitats, roadsides, fields, and riverbanks</habitat>
    <range>Throughout most of North America</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Asia</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>In early spring, look for upright, unbranched, green shoots that resemble asparagus, but flecked with red, pink, and magenta, and divided by joints below sheathes. Look for them among the previous year's dead stems, which create conspicuous bamboo-like thickets. Later in the spring, and in the summer and fall, look for the four to six inch-long, alternate, toothless, pointed, three-sided leaves, and lacy spikes of small white flowers or seeds.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This tall, bushy, bamboo-like invasive Asian perennial creates stands of reddish, bamboo-like shoots with a wonderfully sour flavor, in early spring.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Growing 0.5 to 1.25 inches wide, the upright, unbranched, young, green shoots are dappled with red, pink, and magenta, beginning in the middle of early spring. Whitish, papery sheaths grow upward from regularly spaced joints. Later on, the tall, hollow, conspicuous, woody, jointed mature stems grow nine to 12 feet tall, and create what looks like a bamboo thicket. The dead stalks persist through the winter and into the following spring.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Shaped like bulging triangles, the large, alternate, pointed, toothless leaves, with flat bases and pointed tips, grow to four to six inches long and 2.5 to 4.25 inches wide.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Hundreds of tiny, attractive-looking, greenish-white flowers grow on many long, lacy spikes in the summer, to be replaced by many tiny, three-sided, smooth, beige, papery fruits in autumn. Each contains one tiny, hard, brown seed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;An underground network of interconnected rhizomes is the bane of many gardeners' existence.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Upright, unbranched, jointed, green shoots in early spring spotted with red, pink, and magenta&lt;br /&gt;•Whitish sheaths above the joints&lt;br /&gt;•Skeleton's of the previous year's growth of hollow, jointed, woody, bamboo-like stalks, persisting into the following spring&lt;br /&gt;•Smooth-edged, bulging-triangular leaves, four to six inches long and 2.5 to 4.25 inches wide, with pointed tips and straight bases&lt;br /&gt;•Long spikes of tiny, white flowers, followed by small, smooth, papery fruits, arising from the leaf axils</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Break or cut off the shoots near ground level, discard the inedible leaves, and bag. Those six to eight inches tall are best—you can collect a lot in a very short period of time, and you don't have to peel them. Smaller ones are more labor intensive to collect, while larger shoots tend to get tough rinds, which you need to peel off.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;By the time the shoots reach four feet tall, only the tops are tender enough to peel and eat. Also, the flesh becomes thinner, so there's increasingly more work for less food, until they become completely inedible in mid-spring.</harvesting>
    <cooking>Discard the leaves and chop or slice the intensely sour young shoots. Use them sparingly in fruit dishes, to contrast the fruit's sweet flavor, the same way people use rhubarb, a relative. A 10 to 1 ratio works well. The shoots taste great in pies, cobblers, cakes, and pastries. Or incorporate a small proportion into applesauce.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The shoots are also excellent in larger quantities as a sour addition to soups, stews, and casseroles, especially recipes with bland and creamy ingredients, i.e., potatoes or squash. They even slightly thicken such recipes, the way okra does. And they're wonderful in ice creams and sorbets (similar to lemon sorbet), as well as in puddings and jams.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Before the larger shoots get tough, you can poke in a chopstick to punch through the membrane separating segments of the peeled shoots, insert a sweet or savory stuffing, and bake, with or without a sauce. Using Italian ingredients, I make Knot Ziti (no, I really did, and it's in my &lt;i&gt;Wild Vegan Cookbook&lt;/i&gt; too, believe it or knot!)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You usually discard the rinds of older shoots, but you can also substitute them for orange rind and cook them in sweetened orange juice thickened with agar to make Knot Marmalade.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are thousands of recipes that require sour ingredients. Use your imagination, and I'm sure you'll come up with some wonderfully original ideas that can turn into some awesome recipes.</cooking>
    <nutrition>Japanese knotweed shoots provide vitamins A and C, the antioxidant flavonoid rutin, and the minerals potassium, phosphorus, zinc, and manganese. It’s also an excellent source of resveratrol, also found in the skin of red grapes and in red wine, which lowers LDL (bad) cholesterol, and reduces the risk of heart disease.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>Large quantities may act as a gentle laxative, like rhubarb. This mucilaginous vegetable is also very soothing to the stomach and intestines, and its mild acidity helps break up fat and stimulate digestion.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In addition to lowering the risk of cardiovascular disease, Japanese knotweed's resveratrol may delay the onset of Alzheimer’s disease, or slow its progression. Normally, glial cells in the brain support the neurons, but in Alzheimer’s disease, an accumulation of characteristic amyloid plaques signal these helper cells to kill the neurons instead. The research is preliminary, but resveratrol seems to block this deadly signal.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In addition, extracts of this plant have shown anti-tumor activity. It might turn out to help treat cancer, or lower the risk of coming down with it.</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>This roots of this plant can be deadly, but only to gardeners. Once the rhizomes get permanently established in the gardens, there follows a period of torturous struggle, until the exhausted gardener dies of aggravation!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Don't eat large quantities of Japanese knotweed raw. It has much more oxalic acid than cooked knotweed, and this may cause problems. </cautions>
    <similarPlants>Giant knotweed (&lt;i&gt;P. sachalinense&lt;/i&gt;) is similar to Japanese knotweed, but significantly larger and much less common. You use both plants the same way.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Wild asparagus shoots, also edible, of course, have no sheathes or reddish flecks, and the leaves, flowers, and fruits are completely different.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Fleeceflower, Himalayan Fleece Vine, Monkeyweed, Hancock's Curse, Elephant Ears, Pea Shooters, Donkey Rhubarb, Sally Rhubarb, Japanese Bamboo, American Bamboo, Mexican Bamboo</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>The shoots of this despised invasive species add a wonderful sourness to main courses and desserts, and they're super-healthful.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Giant Knotweed Shoot, Wild Asparagus</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>157</id>
      <title>Knot Pudding</title>
      <slug>knot-pudding</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <directions>Knot Pudding	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This pudding came out so well, I entered it into my computer while I was still eating it. Tasty and simple, the ingredients balance each other perfectly. The knotweed is sour, the raisins and stevia are sweet, the tapioca makes it creamy, and the other flavorings fit in just as they're supposed to. Serve it hot or cold.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;8 cups soy-rice milk, nut milk, or oat milk&lt;br /&gt;2 cup Japanese knotweed shoots, sliced&lt;br /&gt;1 cup raisins&lt;br /&gt;1 cup tapioca pearls&lt;br /&gt;2 tsp. liquid stevia&lt;br /&gt;2 tsp. vanilla extract&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. orange extract&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. nutmeg, ground&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. salt&lt;br /&gt;1 cup raspberries or other berries	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Bring all ingredients except the raspberries to a boil in a heavy saucepan over medium heat, stirring constantly.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Reduce the heat to low and simmer, uncovered, 30 minutes, stirring often.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Serve topped with the fresh berries.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 6 to 8&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation time: 10 minutes&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cooking time: 30 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>158</id>
      <title>1)Japanese Knotweed Shoots</title>
      <slug>1japanese-knotweed-shoots</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>The nodes and joints of both the smaller, younger shoot and the older one are dappled with red, but bulging-triangular to arrow-shaped, smooth-edged, alternate leaves are already developing on the older shoot.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T891x1793-14776.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>159</id>
      <title>3)Japanese Knotweed Leaf, Flowers, and Skeleton</title>
      <slug>3japanese-knotweed-leaf,-flowers,-and-skeleton</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>The spike of small white flowers emerges from the axil of the smooth-edged, three-sided, bulging, pointed leaf. The spikes persist, along with the zigzag of dead, jointed stems, through the winter and into the following spring.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/JapaneseKnotweedDrawings.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>160</id>
      <title>2)A Stand of Japanese Knotweed Shoots</title>
      <slug>2a-stand-of-japanese-knotweed-shoots</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>These green, jointed shoots, flecked with red, magenta, and pink, come up in dense stands among the bamboo-like remnants of the previous year's plants. Whitish sheaths grow above each of the joints, and the developing leaves' margins are still inrolled.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/JapaneseKnotweedShoots.2.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>0</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>161</id>
      <title>4)Japanese Knotweed Flowers and Seeds</title>
      <slug>4japanese-knotweed-flowers-and-seeds</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>The spikes of tiny white flowers emerge from the leaf axils, which also give rise to the smooth-edged, pointed, alternate leaves shaped like bulging triangles.  And the seeds, encased in winged, papery cases, look like tiny kasha groats, befitting this related member of the buckwheat family.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/JapaneseKnotweedLeavesFlowers.Seeds.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>163</id>
      <title>5)Japanese Knotweed Skeletons</title>
      <slug>5japanese-knotweed-skeletons</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>Japanese knotweed's branched, jointed, reddish-brown skeleton, still retaining some of its seeds on terminal racemes, persists through the winter. Note their locations so you can return in early spring and scrounge around for new shoots emerging from perennial rhizomes at the skeletons' bases.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/JapaneseKnotweed.Skeleton.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>164</id>
    <title>Lady's Thumb</title>
    <slug>ladys-thumb</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Polygonum persicaria&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family: &lt;i&gt;Polygonaceae&lt;/i&gt;, the knotweed or smartweed family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>165</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.32560500 1291972540</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <annual>1</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>0</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>166</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.34171200 1291972540</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>167</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.35791600 1291972540</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>You can eat lady's thumb leaves from mid-spring through mid-fall.</season>
    <habitat>Full or partial sun, disturbed habitats, roadsides, parks, meadows, stream banks, railroads, gardens, lawns, and meadows—especially where there's low, wet ground.</habitat>
    <range>Most of the US and Canada</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Europe</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for stands of medium-sized plants with alternate, lance-shaped leaves, sometimes with a central chevron and a terminal cylindrical cluster of tiny, pink flowers. A fringe of hairs grow above the nodes on the stem.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This especially common, easy to recognize edible plant with upright clusters of small, pink flowers, grows nearly everywhere. [-Usually] Growing with slender, erect, branching stems, it reaches from one to 2.5 feet tall, and usually creates dense stands.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The pointed, lance-shaped leaves grow from 1.5 to 4.5 inches long. A slightly darkened triangular spot (chevron), the "lady's thumbprint," often appears toward the leaf's center.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Swollen, reddish-tinged nodes grow along the stem at regular intervals. A sheath connected to the very short, reddish leaf stalk wraps around the stem and a fringe of very short hairs grows from the top of the sheath.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Conspicuous terminal clusters up to 1.5 inches long, consisting of tiny, pink (sometimes white) flowers grow in dense, narrow racemes up to 1.5 inches long.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This plant has both fibrous roots and a shallow taproot.&lt;br /&gt;</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•A medium-sized upright, branching plant with alternate, smooth-edged, lance-shaped leaves 1.5 to 4.5 inches long&lt;br /&gt;•Narrow upper racemes of tiny pink flowers up to 1.5 inches long&lt;br /&gt;•Stem usually close to 1.5 to 2.5 feet tall, divided by reddish-tinged nodes from which arises a sheath fringed with very short hairs.</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Hold down bunches of plants with one hand and strip off the leaves with the other. You may want to discard the flowers. Most people don't care for them, though kids, who like the color, might. The stems are mostly too tough to eat.</harvesting>
    <cooking>Lady's thumb leaves are very mild-tasting. I tell young kids that they taste like lettuce, then suggest "Lettuce try some," and they usually love them. Adults, on the other hand, often find them bland, sometimes suggesting that they're as tasteless as my jokes, but they go well in salads or sandwiches to contrast and offset our many strong-tasting wild greens.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You can also sauté them with other more flavorful ingredients, or add them in soups, stews, and casseroles. They cook in about 10 minutes.</cooking>
    <nutrition></nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>Although people tried using this plant inconsistently for disparate problems in the past, it never seems to have been become valuable, and it isn't currently being used very much, if at all, in herbal medicine.&lt;br /&gt;</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes>0</hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Don't confuse lady's thumb with Lady's Fingers™! This junk food contains refined carbohydrates such as white flour and white sugar, plus artificial flavors and colors, which, when consumed in excess, contribute to the wide range of epidemic chronic illnesses so common in the developed world today. Fortunately, Lady's Fingers™ grow only in supermarkets and convenience stores.</cautions>
    <similarPlants>Lady's thumb is a member of the smartweed family (&lt;i&gt;Polygonum spp.&lt;/i&gt;) Other smartweeds grow larger than lady's thumb and bear white or pink flowers, but lack the characteristic fringe of very short hairs above the sheaths on lady's thumb's stems. Also called smartass or water pepper, these nonpoisonous plants may make you smarter—many are so acrid, they'll make your mouth smart so much that you'll become smart enough never to eat them again! Nevertheless, some people use them in small amounts in place of hot pepper. If you're daring, you may safely chew a bit of a leaf on the tip of your tongue before spitting it out, to see if you like the flavor (you probably won't!) Pennsylvania smartweed is typical of this group.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Persicaria, Redleg, Spotted Lady's Thumb, Gambetta, Adam's Plaster</commonNames>
    <common>1</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>The mild-flavored leaves of this ubiquitous, easy-to-recognize plant, offset the stronger flavors of other wild greens in salads and cooked side dishes or entrées.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant></medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Pennsylvania Smartweed</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon></veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>168</id>
      <title>1)Chonce (From &lt;i&gt;The Wild Vegan Cookbook&lt;/i&gt;, by "Wildman" Steve Brill)</title>
      <slug>1chonce-from-&lt;i&gt;the-wild-vegan-cookbook&lt;i&gt;,-by-wil</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <directions>This unusual hot seasoning includes ingredients associated with Indian, Mediterranean, and health food cuisines. Even plain tasting leaves like lady's thumb won't be bland when you season them with chonce. Add it to soups, grains, spreads, or sauces to enhance their flavor. Take a chonce and try it!	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3 tbs. peanut oil&lt;br /&gt;3 tbs. corn oil or flax seed oil&lt;br /&gt;2 tsp. whole cumin seeds&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. crushed red pepper&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup fresh basil, chopped; or 4 tsp. dried basil, ground&lt;br /&gt;1 tbs. garlic, chopped&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. coriander, ground&lt;br /&gt;6 tbs. brewer’s yeast&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. cloves, ground&lt;br /&gt;1 tsp. tamari soy sauce	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Cook the cumin seeds and crushed red pepper in the peanut oil and corn oil over low heat 2 to 3 minutes, stirring constantly.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Add the basil and garlic, and cook another minute, stirring often.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Add the remaining ingredients, remove the pan from the heat, and allow everything to cook in the hot pan another 2 minutes, stirring often.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Makes 1/2 cup&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation and cooking time: 10 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <recipe>
      <id>169</id>
      <title>2)Chauncey's Squash Soup</title>
      <slug>2chaunceys-squash-soup</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <directions>Chauncey’s Squash Soup	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Using my Chonce recipe as a seasoning, this five ingredient recipe gets a 10!	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3 cups vegetable stock&lt;br /&gt;2 cups cooked squash&lt;br /&gt;2 cups lady's thumb leaves&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup mellow miso&lt;br /&gt;1/4 cup Chonce	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Bring all ingredients to a boil in a saucepan, reduce the heat to low, and simmer 5 minutes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Purée; in a blender, beginning at low speed, and hold down the blender cover with a towel at first, to prevent eruption.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 4&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation/cooking time: 10 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn>http://dev.winterroot.net/deepwinter/foraging/cms#pageId-168</dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>171</id>
      <title>2)Immature Lady's Thumb</title>
      <slug>2immature-ladys-thumb</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>Faint, dark chevrons mark the center of the short-stalked, lance-shaped, pointed, hairless, alternate leaves.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T1508x1569-18952.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>172</id>
      <title>3)Lady's Thumb—side view</title>
      <slug>3ladys-thumb—side-view</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>The raceme of tiny, pink flowers at the top of the jointed stalk is typical of this plant. So are the fringes of short hairs above the sheathes on the stem, and the short-stalked, alternate, lance-shaped, smooth-edged leaves. </caption>
      <poisonous>0</poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Lady'sThumb.Side.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>0</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>173</id>
      <title>4)Lady's Thumb Stand</title>
      <slug>4ladys-thumb-stand</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>Lady's thumb usually grows in dense stands, displaying many upright racemes of tiny, pink flowers high above the leaves, to attract pollinating insects. The smooth-edged, hairless, lance-shaped, alternate leaves are edible and abundant, if not excitingly flavored.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T1000x750-18224.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>174</id>
      <title>5)Lady's Thumb Flowers</title>
      <slug>5ladys-thumb-flowers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>The striking pink color of these small flowers, arranged cylindrically on a raceme, make a stand of these plants otherwise inconspicuous plants noticeable.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Lady'sThumbFlowers.jpg</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>175</id>
      <title>6)Lady's Thumb's Fringed Sheath</title>
      <slug>6ladys-thumbs-fringed-sheath</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>The sheathes wrapped around the stems' nodes are fringed with very short hairs, distinguishing lady's thumb from it's less-than-tasty relatives.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Lady'sThumbSheath.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>177</id>
    <title>Lamb's-quarters</title>
    <slug>lambs-quarters1</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Chenopodium album&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family: &lt;i&gt;Chenopodium&lt;/i&gt;, the goosefoots family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>178</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.74841400 1291972540</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <annual>1</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>0</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>179</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.78156200 1291972540</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>180</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.79875400 1291972540</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>0</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>1</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>1</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>1</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>1</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>1</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>1</earlyFall>
      <midFall>1</midFall>
      <lateFall>1</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>The leaves are in season from mid-spring through mid-fall, the seeds in late fall</season>
    <habitat>Rich soil, sunny or partially shaded habitats, disturbed habitats, roadsides, fields, agricultural land, edge habitats, parks</habitat>
    <range>Throughout North America</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Native to North America and Europe, the seeds are so small, a muddy-footed migrating bird blown of course by a storm could have transported it across the Atlantic either way in prehistoric times.</placeOfOrigin>
    <native>1</native>
    <howToSpot>Look for a tall, branching, hairless odorless plant with diamond-shaped leaves that are mealy white underneath and dense spikes of tiny, green flowers toward the top branches.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This common, odorless annual, with many branching stems is one of our best wild vegetables. It usually grows from three to five feet tall, (sometimes up to 10 feet), with slender, grooved stems often tinged with red—especially next to the leaf axils.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Lambs-quarters leaves surprising take two forms. Mealy whitish underneath, the alternate, diamond-shaped, wavy toothed, mature leaves you see most of the time grow up to four inches long. The youngest leaves at the tips of the branches, on the other hand, are much smaller, linear, and white all over. The leaf stalks grow to about half the length of the leaves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Tiny, green, inconspicuous, bad-tasting, ball-like flowers grow in short, dense spikes in the upper leaf axils and at the plant’s tip, in the summer and fall, eventually turning reddish-brown. By late fall, as many as 75,000 tiny, shiny, cylindrical black seeds per plant grow inside.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Branching plant three to five feet tall or more&lt;br /&gt;•Diamond-shaped, coarsely toothed mature leaves with mealy white undersides&lt;br /&gt;•Linear, young leaves, glistening white all over&lt;br /&gt;•Dense spikes of small, green, spherical flowers on the upper leaf axils&lt;br /&gt;•Dense spikes of small, green, spherical fruits on the upper leaf axils, turning reddish in autumn&lt;br /&gt;•Ripe fruits filled with tiny black seeds,&lt;br /&gt;•Virtually no odor&lt;br /&gt;</positiveId>
    <harvesting>To harvest the leaves, pinch off the whole very young plant while it's a few inches tall, and the stem is still tender enough to break easily. Strip off the leaves of older plants with your fingers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Compared to amaranth, it's more difficult to get a good harvest of these seeds, so look for the dead plants in late fall where they're tall and very abundant. Clip off large numbers of seed clusters with kitchen scissors, pruning shears, or a pocket knife. Stuff them into paper supermarket shopping bags and let them dry out a couple of weeks if necessary (you can store them indefinitely this way).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rub the dry seed heads (this works with fresh seed heads too, but it's less efficient) over a bowl to loosen the seeds. Transfer them to a tray or cookie sheet and blow a fan across the tray over a sink, or outdoors, to get rid of the chaff. Use the seeds immediately, or store indefinitely in tightly closed jars.</harvesting>
    <cooking>Lamb's-quarters leaves taste somewhat like its relative, spinach. Use them, and very young whole plants, like spinach—raw, saut&amp;#233ed;, steamed, simmered in soups, baked in quiches, or in any recipe that calls for raw or cooked greens. They cook in 5 to 10 minutes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cook the nutty flavored seeds as you would a grain: Boil them in water to cover for about 15 minutes, or until the water is absorbed and the seeds are soft, like rice. You may use soy-, nut-, or oat milk instead of water, plus fresh or dried fruit, sweet herbs (i.e., mint, cinnamon, ginger), and a sweetener, to make a sweet hot cereal. To make the seeds more nutty tasting, toast them in a pan over medium a few minutes, until they pop, stirring very often, before adding the liquid.</cooking>
    <nutrition>Lamb's-quarters leaves provide more vitamin A, calcium, potassium, and iron than anything you can buy. They also contain B-complex vitamins and vitamin C, as well as many trace minerals.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The seeds provide protein, calcium, phosphorus, potassium, and niacin.</nutrition>
    <medicinalUses></medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes>1</hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Sometimes lamb's-quarters' leaves are blotched with red. This indicates insect damage. There's even a tiny leaf miner that burrows between the top and bottom surface of the leaves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Don't eat these marred leaves, especially if you're a vegetarian! Also, avoid plants growing in soil polluted with nitrates, which they can pick up and pass on to you, causing nitrate poisoning.</cautions>
    <similarPlants>Lamb's-quarters has some similar-looking, edible relatives that you can use the same way as lamb's-quarters:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Strawberry blight (&lt;i&gt;C. capitatum&lt;/i&gt;) has more triangular leaves than lambs-quarters’—sometimes even arrow shaped, with more of the rounded flowers, and mild-flavored, bright red fruits.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Poverty weed (&lt;i&gt;Monolepsis nuttalliana&lt;/i&gt;) is a fleshy, branching, sprawling annual that grows up to one foot tall, with lance-shaped, alternate, mealy-textured leaves about 0.5 to 2.5 inches long, usually irregularly toothed but sometimes smooth, with a pair of lobes at the bases. Its brown fruits are flattened. It grows in alkaline or dry soil from the eastern edge of the Great Plains to California, and from Southern Canada to Mexico.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Orache (&lt;i&gt;Atriplex patula&lt;/i&gt;) is a salty tasting edible that grows near the seashore and in salty, alkaline soil throughout the country, with arrow-shaped instead of diamond-shaped leaves. Much touted by other authors, I've always found it to have an unpleasantly bitter aftertaste. Maybe this uninspiring plant is better cooked, or other &lt;i&gt;Atriplex&lt;/i&gt; species taste better. Or perhaps all the non-foraging botanists who wrote those foraging books never tried it!</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes>Epazote is edible when used as a seasoning, but poisonous when eaten in large quantities, as you would with lamb's-quarters. However, although it branches and its flower clusters look similar to lamb's-quarters', its strong, resinous odor alone will distinguish it from the nearly odorless lamb's-quarters. Also, its leaves are oblong to lance-shaped, without powdery-white undersides, unlike lamb's-quarters' diamond-shaped leaves with powdery white undersides.</poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Fat-hen, Goosefoot, White Goosefoot, Nickel Greens, Pigweed, Dungweed, Bathua</commonNames>
    <common>0</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>This common, widespread, easy to recognize "weed" is even more tasty and nutritious than its relative, spinach.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser>1</teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant></medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Orache, Epazote</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated>Epazote</poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon>1</veryCommon>
    <recipe>
      <id>181</id>
      <title>Creamed Lamb's-quarters</title>
      <slug>creamed-lambs-quarters</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <directions>Creamed Lamb’s-Quarters	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Here’s a variation of a classic American spinach recipe made using lamb’s-quarters, and further transformed by vegan ingredients replacing the cream.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2 cups lamb’s-quarters or spinach, chopped&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. silken tofu&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. water&lt;br /&gt;2 tbs. corn or flax seed oil&lt;br /&gt;1 tbs. lecithin granules&lt;br /&gt;1/8 tsp. liquid stevia&lt;br /&gt;4 cloves of garlic, peeled but not cut&lt;br /&gt;1/2 tsp. salt&lt;br /&gt;1/4 tsp. black pepper, ground&lt;br /&gt;1/8 tsp. nutmeg	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Purée the water, tofu, corn oil, lecithin, and stevia in a blender.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2. Combine with the remaining ingredients in a saucepan, cover, and cook over low heat until just wilted.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Remove and discard the garlic.	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Serves 4 to 6&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Preparation/cooking time: 20 minutes</directions>
      <dependsOn></dependsOn>
    </recipe>
    <plantImage>
      <id>182</id>
      <title>1)Lamb's-quarters in Flower</title>
      <slug>1lambs-quarters-in-flower</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>Lamb's-quarters branching stem already has diamond-shaped, full-grown leaves, (left), similar to older leaves of mature plants. The younger leaves at the mature plant's tip (right) are more narrow, almost linear, growing among slender spikes of tiny, inconspicuous, wind-pollinated flowers. All the leaves have wavy margins, virtually no odor, and great flavor.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Lamb'sQuartersDrawings.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>1</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>183</id>
      <title>3)Lamb's-quarters Leaves—from below</title>
      <slug>3lambs-quarters-leaves—from-below</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>The diamond-shaped, wavy toothed, mature leaves, with leaf stalks half the length of the leaves, are distinctly mealy white underneath. The tiny, immature leaf, at the tip, is more linear, and white on both sides.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Lamb'sQuartersUnderside1.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>184</id>
      <title>2)Large Lamb's-quarters</title>
      <slug>2large-lambs-quarters</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>The reddish, ridged stem with lots of branches, and the diamond-shaped leaves twice as long as the leaf stalks, plus the leaves' whitish undersides, show what you need to know to recognize this plant.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T860x1744-16953.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>185</id>
      <title>6)Lamb's-quarters Flowers</title>
      <slug>6lambs-quarters-flowers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>Many dense spikes of tiny, green, spherical flowers, powdered with white, arise from the leaf axils. Wind pollinated, they need to be numerous, but since they're not attracting pollinators, they don't need to be large or showy.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T516x400-17050.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>186</id>
      <title>4)Young Lamb's-quarters Leaves</title>
      <slug>4young-lambs-quarters-leaves</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>The youngest leaves are whitish all over. When they get a little larger, they will become diamond-shaped rather than linear.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T1756x1945-17509.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>187</id>
      <title>5)Lamb's-quarters Stand</title>
      <slug>5lambs-quarters-stand</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:40</dateadded>
      <caption>This plant often grows dense stands that make harvesting easy. And the branches are loaded with wavy toothed, diamond-shaped (linear when young), alternate leaves, whitish underneath, making this weedy-looking plant easy to spot.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/T1308x1444-16970.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>190</id>
    <title>Mugwort</title>
    <slug>mugwort</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Artemisia vulgaris&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family &lt;i&gt;Asteraceae  (Compositae)&lt;/i&gt;, the astor or composite family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>191</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.18733300 1291972541</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
      <annual>0</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>1</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible>
      <id>192</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.20221200 1291972541</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible>
      <id>193</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.21819700 1291972541</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
      <earlySpring>1</earlySpring>
      <midSpring>0</midSpring>
      <lateSpring>0</lateSpring>
      <earlySummer>0</earlySummer>
      <midSummer>0</midSummer>
      <lateSummer>0</lateSummer>
      <earlyFall>0</earlyFall>
      <midFall>0</midFall>
      <lateFall>0</lateFall>
      <winter>0</winter>
      <allYear></allYear>
    </primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>You can cook the leaves in early spring, and make tea with any part above-ground part of the plant from early spring to late fall.</season>
    <habitat>Sunny and partially shaded habits, nitrogenous soil, disturbed habitats, old fields, meadows, roadsides, ditches, parks, edges, and thickets</habitat>
    <range>Eastern North America, southern Canada, the Pacific Northwest, and California</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>Eurasia</placeOfOrigin>
    <native></native>
    <howToSpot>Look for dense colonies of tall, downy plants (or a ground cover where it's been mowed) with deeply cut lower and linear upper leaves, whitish underneath,[and] dense clusters of tiny, inconspicuous, green flowers. Scratch and sniff for an intense grassy medicinal odor when crushed.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>Growing from two to 12 feet tall with a stem often tinged with red and purple that becomes somewhat woody, this very common, downy, fragrant, Eurasian colonial invasive perennial takes over sunny, open areas anywhere it's been introduced.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The pointed, alternate, stalked, toothed, mature leaves, dark green on top, are covered with mats of tiny whitish hairs underneath. Two  to four inches long and one to three inches wide, they look a little like parsley—partially divided and subdivided many times, as though snipped with scissors. The upper leaves are less divided, sometimes linear, and often stalkless.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In the summer and fall, many tiny, green, cottony flowers, sometimes reddish-brown at the tips, grow on long, upright, leafy panicles. The tiny green fruits release even smaller achenes attached to tiny, white parachutes into the air, like dandelions, which belong to the same large family.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The root system consists of woody rhizomes that secrete herbicides to kill competitors, ensuring that mugwort often grows in monocultures of dense stands.</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Dense stands of medium-sized to tall plants with deeply lobed, stalked mature leaves, and linear immature leaves&lt;br /&gt;•Persistent woody skeletons of previous years' growth&lt;br /&gt;•Leaves with tiny, matted, whitish-green hairs underneath&lt;br /&gt;•Many tiny greenish flowers growing on long, upright spikes&lt;br /&gt;•A strong odor like tarragon and camphor when crushed</positiveId>
    <harvesting>To use as food, pinch off the young plants with your fingers. For tea or for dreaming, break, strip, or clip off any of the above-ground parts of the plant.</harvesting>
    <cooking>This is a bitter relative of wormwood and not the best-tasting of wild foods. Nonetheless, Korea people dip the young leaves in batter when the plants are but a few inches tall, and deep-fry this. In China and Japan, mugwort's used to flavor rice cakes, and in Japan, it's used in making soba (buckwheat) noodles.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You can also stuff a pillow with the soft parts of the plants. It gives some people vivid dreams, although they may or may not be pleasant.</cooking>
    <nutrition></nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>A major herb in traditional Chinese medicine, mugwort contains the fragrant, volatile oil psilostachyin, as well as biologically active ketones and alkaloids. Dried mugwort leaves and roots are used for moxa treatments, where it's burned in cups placed over acupuncture points. And it's served with fatty meals in China and Eastern Europe, to stimulate the secretion of bile to help digest the fat.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Chinese also use an infusion or tincture of the leaves and roots for anxiety, stress, insomnia, mild depression, irritability, restlessness, and menstrual problems—taken twice a day starting a week before menstruation, a strong infusion of the leaves greatly reduces or eliminates PMS symptoms and cramps. I can attest the this personally: Ever since I learned this plant, I've never had a cramp!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Mugwort contains the controversial substance thujone, a possible hallucinogen well-known for its presence in notorious alcoholic beverage, absinthe, made with mugwort's relative, absinthe wormwood (&lt;i&gt;A. absinthium&lt;/i&gt;). So many deaths were attributed to absinthe in the late 19th and early 20th centuries that it had been banned worldwide. Nowadays those deaths are attributed to plain old alcoholism, because there's too little thujone in absinthe to cause poisoning, and the "green fairy" is legal again. Furthermore, mugwort is so bitter, it's unlikely anyone could possibly consume enough to cause harm.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mugwort is also closely related to ragweed (&lt;i&gt;Artemesia spp.&lt;/i&gt;), a major cause of hay fever. Although I don't have hay fever, just smelling mugwort gives me a bad headache, so I certainly don't eat it or cook with it. Avoid the plant altogether if you have hay fever or are allergic to ragweed.</cautions>
    <similarPlants>Common ragweed (&lt;i&gt;Ambrosia artemisiifolia&lt;/i&gt;) looks a little like mugwort, but its leaves are more finely dissected, it's not fragrant, and the leaves aren't light-colored underneath.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Chrysanthemums (&lt;i&gt;Chrysanthemum spp.&lt;/i&gt;) look a little like mugwort, but their leaves are much larger, they're not light green underneath, they only grow in gardens, and they have large, showy flowers.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>Moxa, Felon Herb, Chrysanthemum Weed, Wild Wormwood, Old uncle Henry, Sailor's Tobacco, Naughty Man, Old Man, St. John's Plant</commonNames>
    <common>1</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive>1</invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>Mainly a traditional east Asian medicinal herb, putting this plant under your pillow can give you vivid dreams!</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser></teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated></similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon></veryCommon>
    <plantImage>
      <id>194</id>
      <title>2)Mature Mugwort Leaf</title>
      <slug>2mature-mugwort-leaf</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
      <caption>Mugwort's toothed leaves are deeply divided into many lobes, and fine, matted hairs give their undersides a whitish appearance.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/MugwortLeaf.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>196</id>
      <title>4)Mugwort Flowers</title>
      <slug>4mugwort-flowers</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
      <caption>The young, upper leaves, still whitish underneath, have fewer lobes than the lower ones. And the tiny, reddish-brown-tipped, greenish, wind-pollinated flowers grow in quantity on panicles arising from the leaf axils.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/MugwortInFlower.tif</image>
      <primaryImage></primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>197</id>
      <title>3)Mugwort Leaf Underside</title>
      <slug>3mugwort-leaf-underside</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
      <caption>The deeply lobed, toothed leaves look whitish underneath due to mats of tiny hairs.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Mugwort Top.2.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage>0</primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
    <plantImage>
      <id>198</id>
      <title>4)Mugwort Stand</title>
      <slug>4mugwort-stand</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
      <caption>Mugwort grows in dense stands, taking over habitats. The tall plant's deeply lobed leaves, whitish underneath, and the many, tiny, green flowers make it easy to spot, even without smelling it.</caption>
      <poisonous></poisonous>
      <image>application/media/Mugwort Stand in Flower.tif</image>
      <primaryImage>1</primaryImage>
      <primaryIdentificationImage></primaryIdentificationImage>
    </plantImage>
  </plant>
  <plant>
    <id>199</id>
    <title>Pineapple Weed</title>
    <slug>pineapple-weed</slug>
    <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
    <scientificName>&lt;i&gt;Matricaria discoidea&lt;/i&gt;, formerly &lt;i&gt;M. matricarioides&lt;/i&gt;</scientificName>
    <group>Family &lt;i&gt;Asteraceae  (Compositae)&lt;/i&gt;, the astor or composite family</group>
    <plantType>
      <id>200</id>
      <title></title>
      <slug>No_Title_0.45545200 1291972541</slug>
      <dateadded>2010-12-10 01:15:41</dateadded>
      <annual>1</annual>
      <biennial>0</biennial>
      <perennialHerbaceous>0</perennialHerbaceous>
      <vine>0</vine>
      <shrub>0</shrub>
      <tree>0</tree>
      <seaweed>0</seaweed>
    </plantType>
    <seasonsEdible></seasonsEdible>
    <primarySeasonsEdible></primarySeasonsEdible>
    <season>Mid-spring through early summer.</season>
    <habitat>Sunny places with poor soil, lawns, parks, gravel roads, walkways, baseball diamonds, cracks in sidewalks, and parking lots</habitat>
    <range>Most of the US and southern Canada</range>
    <placeOfOrigin>US Pacific Coast</placeOfOrigin>
    <native>1</native>
    <howToSpot>Look for small plants with feathery leaves and small, flattened cones of yellow-green composite flowers, growing in very poor, sunny soil. Scratch and sniff for pineapple.</howToSpot>
    <generalInfo>This small, pineapple-scented plant, usually growing only three to 12 inches tall, bears very finely divided, hairless, fern-like, alternate leaves 0.5 to two inches long.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The globular, yellow-green, bluntly cone-shaped, button-like, stalked, composite flower heads grow 0.25 to 0.5 inches across. They're borne in a cup of overlapping bracts on short flower stalks arising from the axils of the upper leaves. The flowers consist of many tiny, tightly packed disk flowers, best viewed under magnification. There are no ray flowers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The fruits are sunflower seed-like achenes, nearly too small to see.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The root system consists of a taproot with secondary fibrous roots.&lt;br /&gt;</generalInfo>
    <positiveId>•Small plant with feathery, fern-like leaves&lt;br /&gt;•Thrives in full sunlight in very poor soil&lt;br /&gt;•Flattened cone-shaped, yellow-green, composite flowers the size of a pencil eraser&lt;br /&gt;•No ray flowers&lt;br /&gt;•Clear pineapple fragrance when crushed or torn&lt;br /&gt;</positiveId>
    <harvesting>Snip the above-ground parts of this tough plant with scissors or a pocket knife. It's hard to break off with your fingers, and you don't want the roots or their accompanying soil</harvesting>
    <cooking>You can add some of the young leaves or flower heads, before they get bitter, to salads, sandwiches, or puddings, where they impart a pleasant pineapple flavor. But the most important use is as a great-tasting infusion. You can use all above-ground parts for this, made from fresh or dried plants.</cooking>
    <nutrition></nutrition>
    <medicinalUses>This is the tea to drink when you've had a really bad day—a strong infusion is excellent for stress-related nervousness, gastric upset, and insomnia. A vegetarian alternative to counting sheep, it will settle a nervous stomach and calm you down enough to improve your chances of falling asleep. You can use it along with linden flowers, which have similar effects, and the two herbs may work even better together.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It has also been used to relieve infected sores, and for fevers, and postpartum anemia, although none of these uses have been scientifically verified.</medicinalUses>
    <hasPoisonousLookalikes></hasPoisonousLookalikes>
    <cautions>Some people are highly allergic to this plant. Avoid it if you have hay fever, or are allergic to its relative, ragweed (&lt;i&gt;Artemisia spp.&lt;/i&gt;)</cautions>
    <similarPlants>Some obstinate people insist that pineapple weed is chamomile (&lt;i&gt;M. recuttia&lt;/i&gt;), a close relative with the same uses. Both plants have similar leaves, but chamomile's a larger plant, with a larger disk that's yellow, not yellow-green. But to really convince the pig-headed, you'll have to point out that chamomile has white ray flowers, which pineapple weed lacks.</similarPlants>
    <poisonousLookalikes></poisonousLookalikes>
    <poisonous></poisonous>
    <poisonousPart></poisonousPart>
    <commonNames>False Chamomile, Disc Mayweed, </commonNames>
    <common>1</common>
    <endangered></endangered>
    <invasive></invasive>
    <foodUses></foodUses>
    <edibleParts></edibleParts>
    <flashcardShortFact>This pineapple-scented relative of chamomile provides a first-rate beverage that's relaxing, is good for indigestion, and helps people get to sleep.</flashcardShortFact>
    <teaser></teaser>
    <primaryHabitats></primaryHabitats>
    <habitats></habitats>
    <ediblePlant>1</ediblePlant>
    <medicinalPlant>1</medicinalPlant>
    <wr_flashcardOverride></wr_flashcardOverride>
    <similarPlantsAssociated>Chamomile</similarPlantsAssociated>
    <poisonousLookalikesAssociated></poisonousLookalikesAssociated>
    <veryCommon></veryCommon>
  </plant>
</plants>
